<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The lot or portion of the righteous A comfortable sermon, preached at the Cathedrall Church of Glocester, vpon the fift day of August: Anno Domini. 1615. By Richard Web, preacher of Gods word at Rodborough in Glocestershyre.</title>
            <author>Webb, Richard, preacher of God's word.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1616</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 130 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14849</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25151</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102699</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838470</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838470</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2851</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14849)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2851)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1121:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The lot or portion of the righteous A comfortable sermon, preached at the Cathedrall Church of Glocester, vpon the fift day of August: Anno Domini. 1615. By Richard Web, preacher of Gods word at Rodborough in Glocestershyre.</title>
                  <author>Webb, Richard, preacher of God's word.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 42 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Tho: Creede, for Roger Iackson, and are to be solde at his shoppe in Fleetstreet, ouer against the Conduit,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1616.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Pages 34-5 misnumbered 36 and 33.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2851:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2851:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE LOT OR PORTION OF THE RIGHTEOVS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> COMFORTABLE <hi>SERMON, PREACHED AT THE Cathedrall Church of</hi> Gloceſter, <hi>vpon the fift day of Auguſt: Anno Domini.</hi> 1615.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Richard Web,</hi> Preacher of Gods word, at <hi>Rodborough</hi> in <hi>Gloceſterſhyre.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iob. 13. verſ. 15.16.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <l>Loe, though hee ſlay mee, yet will I trust in him,</l>
               <l>and I will reprooue my wayes in his ſight.</l>
               <l>He ſhall be my ſaluation alſo. For the Hypocrite</l>
               <l>ſhall not come before him.</l>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Tho: Creede,</hi> for <hi>Roger Iackſon,</hi> and are to be ſolde at his ſhoppe in Fleetſtreet, ouer againſt the Conduit. 1616.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:2851:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2851:2"/>
            <head>TO THE MOST HIGH and mightie King, King <hi>Iames,</hi> King of great <hi>Brittane, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> defender of the true Chriſtian faith: grace and peace from God the <hi>father, and from our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Oſt deare and gratious Soueraigne, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whom I bow in all ſubiectiue manner) I doubt not, but that worthy ſaying of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> a worthy king, is worthily written in the heart of your maieſtie our king, <hi>Rabboth Ranghoth Tſaddic, Vmirrullam Iattſilennu Iehouah.</hi> 1. <hi>Many are the troubles of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, but the Lord deliuereth him out of them all.</hi> Of all the ſtates in the world, your highnes, the onely great ſtate of the world, hath had beſt experience of the truth of this point, your troubles, we know to the griefe of our hearts, haue bene many; and your deliuerances alſo, we know to the comfort of our ſoules, haue bene as many. This ſentence of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, moſt worthy to be written, not only in ſheetes of gold, but alſo in the hearts of all men by the point of a Diamond, was my text vpon the fift of Auguſt laſt paſt: which day was kept ſolemnely by vs in our ſolemne city of <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> to the Honour of your Highnes, and for the triumph of your bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed victory out of <hi>Gowries</hi> wicked conſpiracy. Since that day, I haue bene ſollicited and importuned by friends, that my Sermon might be printed in papers, which then I deſired onely to be imprinted in the hearts of my hearers; which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:2851:3"/>done, I make bold, (if not too bold) to dedicate to your maieſtie, as being your owne, for that it was preached on your day, for your ſake; to your Honour, and by your ſubiect, who is your deuoted ſeruant to death it ſelfe. My hope and hearts deſire is, that as Chriſt rewarded the poore widowes Mite, which was caſt into the treaſury of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, though it were nothing in quantity comparable to the great ſummes of mony, which the rich caſt into the ſame: ſo your highnes will reſpect this litle booke of mine, your poore ſeruant, though it be nothing to thoſe great volumes, which are conſecrated to your maieſtie by the learned <hi>Rabbins</hi> of the land. The almighty bleſſe your highnes, and grant in fauour vnto vs all, that your maieſtie may be euermore in wiſedome moſt admirable like <hi>Daniel:</hi> in courage moſt valiant, like <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid:</hi> in zeale moſt feruent, like <hi>Phinehas:</hi> in godlines moſt ſingular, like <hi>Ioſiah:</hi> in care moſt prouident, like <hi>Ioſeph:</hi> in riches moſt abundant, like <hi>Saloman:</hi> in counſell moſt ſound, like <hi>Achitophell:</hi> in loue moſt kind, like <hi>Ionathan:</hi> in body moſt healthfull, like <hi>Moſes:</hi> in minde moſt ioyfull, like <hi>Simeon:</hi> in raigne amongſt vs in our Engliſh coaſts, moſt long, like <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſes:</hi> And laſtly, that your highnes at the laſt may be carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Angels into the boſome of <hi>Abraham,</hi> like <hi>Lazarus.</hi> And hereunto let all your ſubiects and friends, both domeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call and forraigne, ſay, Amen. And ſo vpon the bended knees of my heart, I aske pardon for this my boldnes, and reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Maieſties moſt humble, and truely deuoted Subiect,</hi> Richard Web.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:2851:3"/>
            <head>The Contents of the Sermon following.</head>
            <list>
               <item>THe Exordium or Praeface.</item>
               <item>The Analyſis, or Paraphraſe.</item>
               <item>The ſumme and parts.</item>
               <item>Foure Questions about the righteous.</item>
               <item>There are Righteous perſons in the world.</item>
               <item>Who they be that are righteous.</item>
               <item>By what meanes men are made righteous.</item>
               <item>The markes whereby Righteous men may be knowne from others.</item>
               <item>Chriſtians must haue a respect to all the commandements of God.</item>
               <item>In all good workes men muſt haue an eye to Gods glorie.</item>
               <item>Godly perſons muſt continue in their godlineſſe to the ende.</item>
               <item>Men muſt loue goodneſſe in others as well as in themſelues, and labour to make others good like vnto themſelues.</item>
               <item>The righteous ſhall haue troubles here in this world.</item>
               <item>God in loue will correct the Righteous.</item>
               <item>The diuell in malice will aſſault the righteous.</item>
               <item>The world in hatred will purſue the righteous.</item>
               <item>There are ſeuen things, wherein righteous perſons paſſe others.</item>
               <item>The end which God doth aime at, in correcting the righteous, is alwayes for their good.</item>
               <item>Afflictions are no ſigne of reiection, but a marke rather of Election, to euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life.</item>
               <item>Comfort &amp; ſuccour muſt be miniſtred vnto the righteous in their troubles.</item>
               <item>Holy perſons muſt prepare their hearts for troubles.</item>
               <item>The preparation that muſt be made againſt troubles, ſtandeth chiefly in the meditation of <hi>3.</hi> things, (viz.) of the neceſſitie of trouble, of the vtilitie of troubles, and of the multiplicitie of thoſe promiſes, which God hath made vnto vs about our troubles.</item>
               <item>The commodities which troubles do bring vnto the righteous, are foure: two belonging to this life; two others, respecting the next life. Godlineſſe and credit for this life. An aſſurance of glory, and a larger meaſure of glorie for the next life.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:2851:4"/>
               <item>The troubles of the righteous are many. Many for the perſons from whome they come: many for the meanes through which they come: many for the times wherein they come: many for the parts to which they come: many for the ſorts by which they come: many luſtly, for the effects which they bring at their comming.</item>
               <item>Sixe cauſes, why the troubles of the righteous are many, (viz:) becauſe their ſinnes are many: their graces many: their enemies many: their bleſſings many: their exerciſes of religion many: and their contentions againſt the world, the fleſh, and the diuell many.</item>
               <item>A comfort to the godly, who haue many troubles.</item>
               <item>The difference between the troubles of the wicked, and the godly, which ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in <hi>3.</hi> things, (viz.) the cauſe of their troubles: the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner of bearing their troubles, &amp; the end or fruite which doth follow vpon their troubles.</item>
               <item>Righteous perſons muſt labour to haue patience, as a moſt needfull thing for them in all their troubles.</item>
               <item>Holy perſons muſt euermore looke for croſſes in this life.</item>
               <item>God will deliuer the righteous out of all their troubles.</item>
               <item>Foure reaſons why God doth ridde the righteous out of their troubles, (viz) his loue towards them: his promiſe vnto them: his feeling with them: and his glory from them: ioyned with their louing truſt in him, and truſting loue towards him.</item>
               <item>GOD muſt haue the onely praiſe of thoſe deliuerances which the righteous haue.</item>
               <item>In all miſeries holy perſons must reſort vnto the Lord, and relye onely vpon him for their deliuerance therefrom.</item>
               <item>A comfort to the Saints againſt all their tribulations.</item>
               <item>GOD doth ſaue his ſometimes by meanes, and ſometimes without meanes, and ſometimes contrary to all meanes.</item>
               <item>A cooling-card to the world, who oppoſe themſelues againſt the righteous.</item>
               <item>The troubles wherein the Kings Maieſtie was in Scotland, by Gowries con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracie, diuided into <hi>3.</hi> parts, togither with his deliuerances fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſame.</item>
               <item>The Kings thanking of God for his victory, and the great reioycing of all the land for his deliuerance.</item>
               <item>A Prayer for the King.</item>
               <item>An Application to the Auditorie, wherein ſixe reaſons are ſet downe, why troubles ſhould not trouble any of them though they be manie.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:2851:4"/>
            <head>THE LOT AND PORTION OF THE <hi>RIGHTEOVS.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Pſalme <hi>34.19.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Many are the troubles of the righteous, but the Lord deliuereth him out of them all.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Oſes,</hi> an holy man of God, ſpeaking to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God, concerning the Inſtitution of the Paſſe-ouer, to be kept at his appointed ſeaſon, from yeare to yeare, ſaith:
<note place="margin">Exod. 13.14.</note> 
               <hi>When thy Sonne ſhall aske thee, What is this? Thou ſhalt ſay vnto him, With a mightie hand the Lord brought vs out of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gipt, out of the houſe of bondage: and in remembrance hereof, wee celebrate this Feast.</hi> In like manner, when your children (right reuerend father, right worſhipfull, and wel beloued brethren in Chriſt Ieſus) ſhall aske of you, what this our aſſemblie meaneth; You ſhall anſwer, that it is, to giue God thankes for that great benefite, which wee receiued at his hands, as on this day, when in his mercie, hee ſaued our King after a mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous manner, and deliuered him out of the hands of bloody and deſperate traitors, who had vowed his death, to the hurt of vs all, and to the harme of Gods whole Church beſides. This is the day,
<note place="margin">Pſalm. 118.24.</note> which the Lord hath made, let vs reioice and be glad therin. Vpon this day God ſhewed vs the light of his gracious countena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and had mercy vpon vs, in preſeruing for vs ſo great a treaſure, ſo good
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:2851:5"/>a gouernour, ſo learned a Maiſter, ſo worthie a King. The Lord graunt, that wee may enioy him many happie yeares, and become moſt thankfull vnto his Maieſtie for him. But to draw to my text; in it you ſhall finde two points, moſt worthy of your obſeruation, and moſt correſpondent vnto this our dayes celebration.</p>
            <p>In the firſt, you ſhall ſee what entertainment you are to expect for heere in this world. In the ſecond, you ſhall behold what fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour you are to look for, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lord your God out of this world. The firſt of theſe will ſhew you you troubles, the latter your deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance from your troubles; and both of them ioyntlie together, will ſhew you both the hands of God: the one like a wound, mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming you, the other, a plaiſter healing you. Oh marke and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der things well. The righteous muſt looke for more troubles then others. And againe, they muſt hope for greater deliuerances then others. Their afflictions heere will bee many, like the Hoaſt of the <hi>Aramites:</hi> and their redemptions alſo will bee as many, like the Hoaſt of the <hi>Iſraelites. Dauid</hi> beeing a righteous man, and one according to Gods owne heart, found this moſt true by his own experience. He had many troubles, yet he was deliuered out of all his troubles. For this cauſe doth hee here (meaſuring as it were, other men by his owne foote) declare vnto vs, what is the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate or condition of all righteous perſons. On the one ſide, hee doth tell vs, that they are ſubiect to manifold troubles and afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. On the other ſide, he doth aſſure vs, that they ſhall not conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue in theſe their troubles and afflictions, but in time conuenient be deliuered out of them all; and that, by the gracious hand of the Lord their God, who doth watch ouer them ſtill for their good. So that the ſpirit of God directed him to thoſe two chiefe things, which make men take their croſſes grieuouſly. One, becauſe they do not look for them before they come: another, becauſe they do not behold their deliuerer fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them, when they are come. The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet doth preuent both theſe, and tell vs, that the righteous ſhall haue many troubles; &amp; that the Lord wil deliuer him out of all his troubles. I pray remember you both the ſentences: how, to wit, you muſt goe through a Sea of troubles: And how then, you ſhall come to an hauen of reſt; that ſo, when any troubles do come on you, they may not trouble you, like other men, who looke not
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:2851:5"/>for their troubles, nor knowe not where to haue a remedie againſt their troubles. Thus you haue heard the <hi>Analyſis;</hi> now marke the ſum &amp; parts. The ſum ſets down the ſtate or condition of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous. The parts are two. The firſt doth note out his miſerie. The ſecond, his deliuerance from his miſerie. His miſerie is deſcribed out two wayes. Firſt, by the nature or quality of it. Then ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by the magnitude or quantitie of it. The nature, or qualitie, in this word, <hi>Troubles.</hi> The magnitude or qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>titie, in the other word, <hi>Many. Many are the troubles of the righteous.</hi> His deliuerance from his miſerie, containes two branches vnder it. The firſt is the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, who doth deliuer him. The ſecond is the thing, from which he is deliuered. The perſon that doth deliuer him, is the Lord. The thing from which hee is deliuered, are all his troubles: but <hi>the Lord deliuereth him out of all his troubles.</hi> Now of theſe in order.</p>
            <p>But before I beginne with them, becauſe the whole,
<note place="margin">Tſaddik.</note>and euery part, doth concerne the <hi>Righteous:</hi> and whatſoeuer is now to be ſpoken, muſt haue a ſecret relation vnto them; neceſſitie and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie doe require of mee, that I ſhould ſpeake a fewe words concerning them. Yet ſpeaking of the righteous, I will not ſpeak of all the things which doe belong to the Righteous. There are foure queſtions, which may iuſtly be moued co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning them. The firſt is, whether there bee any righteous perſons in all the world, yea or no: Seeing <hi>Iohn</hi> doth teach vs, that the whole worlde doth lye in wickednes.
<note n="a" place="margin">Iohn. 5.19.</note> The ſecond is, that if there bee any, who they be: and what they are. The third is: How and by what meanes, they that bee, and are, are made Righteous, ſeeing all by nature are corrupt, and vnrighteous, according to Chriſtes wordes, when hee ſaith: <hi>That which is borne of the fleſh, is fleſh.</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Iohn. 3.6.</note> The fourth and laſt is, by what tokens or ſignes, they that are, and are made righteous, may be knowne from other men, conſidering that they doe liue amongſt others, like men. If I ſhould be long in the opening of theſe things before you, I muſt haue a large time to open them vnto you. But now ſeeing that I muſt meaſure my ſpeech, by the meaſure of the clock, in running his houre, you muſt giue mee leaue to runne ouer theſe pointes, and rather to point at them, then in any point to dwel vpon them. Wherfore referring all theſe matters rather vnto your owne priuate meditation, then pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:2851:6"/>any one of them, by any long declaration. Thus I ſhut vp all in a fewe words, as followeth.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Though the whole world doth lye in wickednes, yet there are righteous perſons in the world: for as the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or world, there, in that place of <hi>Iohn,</hi> doth not note out all men, which are in the world, but the wicked onely, who are the greateſt part of the world, and who alſo are ſcattered ouer all the world, beeing as it were, a world of it ſelfe: So the ſcripture elſe-where doth witnes in many places, that the Lord hath ſome Righteous perſons ſtill here in this world, howſoeuer this world be not worthy of them.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Heb. 11.28.</note> Such an one was <hi>Noah,</hi> of whome it is ſaid, <hi>That hee was a iuſt and vpright man;</hi> and one <hi>that walked with GOD:</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Geneſ 6.9.</note> Such an one was <hi>Iob,</hi> of whom it is ſaid, <hi>that hee was an vpright and iust man, one that feared GOD, and eſchewed euill:</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Iob. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.1.</note> Such an one was <hi>Lot;</hi> of whome it is ſaid, <hi>That hee being righteous,</hi> and <hi>dwelling among the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domites, in ſeeing</hi> and <hi>hearing them, vexed his righteous ſoule from day to day, with their vnlawfull deedes.</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">2. Peter 2.8.</note> Such an one was <hi>Zacharie,</hi> and his wife <hi>Elizabeth:</hi> of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is ſaid, <hi>that both were iuſt before GOD, and walked in all the commandements &amp; admonitions of the Lord, without reproofe.</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Luke. 1.6.</note> Such an one laſtly, is euery faithful man and woman, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the face of the earth: Of whome it is ſaide, <hi>The Righteous doe loue thee.</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Cant. 1.3.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Thoſe that are righteous, and ſuch as are purged from their ſinnes, wherewith they are naturally defiled, and are qualified al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo with new and heauenly graces, to doe ſuch things as are well pleaſing vnto the Lord: They are not only clenſed from their fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe, but are renued alſo, according to the image of God, to walke in his commandements. Surely whoſoeuer faileth in either of theſe, commeth too ſhort of being righteous. For both muſt be ioyned together, in all thoſe, that will be righteous. <hi>Agur</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of the former, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſaith, <hi>There is a generation, that are pure in their owne concey<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp; yet are not waſhed from their filthineſſe.</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Prou. 30.12.</note> And <hi>Iohn</hi> the Apoſtle doth make mention of the latter, in theſe words, <hi>Little children, let no man deceyue you, hee that doth righteouſneſſe, is righteous, as hee is righteous: hee that committeth ſinne, is of the diuell,</hi> and ſo foorth.
<note n="k" place="margin">1. Iohn. 3.7.8.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The meanes whereby men are made righteous, is two-fold.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:2851:6"/>The one is by <hi>Iuſtification,</hi> and the other by <hi>Sanctification.</hi> For there is a righteouſnes of Iuſtification, and a righteouſnes of ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: the one (as it were) to make vs righteous before God; the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to make vs righteous before men. The firſt of theſe is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out vs: the ſecond is within vs. That which is without vs, is from Chriſt; and that which is within vs, is from the ſpirite. The former of theſe, which is the righteouſnes of Chriſt, is apprehended of vs by faith, and made our owne by <hi>Imputation.</hi> The latter of theſe, which is the righteouſnes of the ſpirit, is poſſeſſed of vs by <hi>loue,</hi> &amp; made our owne by <hi>inheſion.</hi> Now both theſe righteouſneſſes muſt concurre to make a man truly righteous to ſaluation, as they did in the <hi>Corinthians:</hi> of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we read thus; <hi>And ſuch were ſome of you, but yee are waſhed, but ye are ſanctified, but ye are iuſtified, in the Name of the Lord Ieſus, and by the ſpirit of our God.</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">1. Cor. 6.11.</note> And ſurely where both theſe are, there may men and women truely be called righteous, though that ſinne doth ſtil remaine, and dwell within them. Firſt, becauſe one manner of righteouſnes is in them, in a full perfection, euen the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt, which is imputed and applyed vnto them by their faith. Then ſecondly, becauſe an other manner of righteouſnes is in them, in the operatiue beginnings of it, euen the righteouſnes of the ſpirit, who doth worke daily within them, and labour to renue them more and more, according to Gods image, wherein they were created at the firſt.</p>
            <p>The markes or ſignes, by the which the righteous may bee knowne from others, are chiefly foure. The firſt is, by the <hi>Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie</hi> of their obedience. For euery righteous man (who is righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous indeed) hath a care of the whole courſe of his life, and lookes reſpectiuely to all the commandements of God. He doth not take libertie in any one ſinne, but ſtriueth to auoyd all ſinnes, nor omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth one good duty, but endeuoureth to performe all good duties. He is not like to <hi>Naaman</hi> the <hi>Syrian,</hi> who profeſſed the true God of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and promiſed to ſerue and worſhip him alone; yet deſired to be borne withall, for one ſpeciall ſinne: which was, to be in the houſe of <hi>Rimmon;</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">2. King. 5.</note> and there to vphold his Maſter, leaning on his hand, and to bowe before that Idoll, whome hee did worſhip. Neither is hee like to <hi>Herod,</hi> who feared <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptist,</hi> reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renced him, heard him gladly, and did many things after his tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:2851:7"/>but yet hee kept ſtill his brothers wife, and would not put her away, according to Gods commandement.
<note n="n" place="margin">Mat. 16.18.</note> But hee is like to <hi>Ioſiah,</hi> who turned to the Lord with all his hart, and with all his ſoule, &amp; with all his ſtrength, according to all the law of <hi>Moſes.</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">2. King 24.25.</note> And vnto <hi>Zacharie,</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> who were iuſt before God, and walked in all the commaundements and ordinances of the Lord, without reproofe.
<note n="p" place="margin">Luk. 1.6.</note> And no maruell. For he doth know full well, that whoſoeuer ſhall keepe the whole Lawe, and yet faileth in one point, hee is guiltie of all.
<note n="q" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 2.10.</note> That a ſhippe, though it be ſound in all partes, ſaue one, and leaketh in no place ſaue onely one: yet it may be drowned by meanes of that one. That the walles of a Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, though they be ſtrong and well fortified in all places ſaue one, and haue no breaches in them, ſaue only one: yet they may be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the enemy by means of that one. That laſtly, a bird, though it be free in all members ſaue one, and be tyde in no member, ſaue onely one, whether legge, or wing, yet may be held faſt, by meanes of that one. Hereof is it, that he doth labor to purge himſelfe from all filthineſſe of the fleſh and ſpirit, and to grow vp vnto full holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in the feare of God, according to <hi>Paules</hi> exhortation to the <hi>Corinthians.</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">2. Cor. 7.1.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond is, by the <hi>end</hi> wherevnto all their works or deeds do tend. For euery righteous man, (who is righteous indeed) hath a ſpeciall eye vnto the praiſe and honour of his God, in all things which he doth take into his hands, according to our Sauiours ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; <hi>Let your light ſo ſhine before men, that they may ſee your good works, and glorifie your Father which is in heauen.</hi>
               <note n="s" place="margin">Mat. 5.16.</note> And after the Apoſtles rule, when he ſaith, <hi>Whether yee eate or drinke, or whatſoeuer elſe ye doe, doe all to the gory of God.</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">1. Cor. 10.31</note>
            </p>
            <p>Surely, though men practiſe neuer ſo many good works, yet if in doing of them, they propound not this ende vnto themſelues, they are not to be accounted righteous men: no more then he is to be eſteemed a good Archer, which can draw a ſtrong Bowe, hath a faire looſe, and doth ſhoote farre, and yet alwayes ſhootes a great way off from the marke. In this regard, the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſies</hi> in the dayes of our Sauiour, were not accounted by him in the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of righteous men, but ſtiled rather of him, by the name of <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites,</hi> becauſe all that good, which they did at any time, was not
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:2851:7"/>for Gods glory, but for their owne praiſe, that they might be ſeene of men. They did faſt, and pray, and giue almes, but all was for to haue a name, &amp; a commendation of the world.
<note n="u" place="margin">Mat. 6.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> In like ſort the Papiſts faile in this point, now in our dayes. For they doe all their good works in a manner to merite thereby, like to hyred ſeruants, and labourers, who worke for their wages, and would doe little or nothing for their Maiſters, vnles they might be well paide for their paines. But Chriſtians muſt acknowledge themſelues not to bee ſeruants, but children, and not children of the bond-woman, but of the free-woman; and that they ought of duety to ſerue the Lord, all the dayes of their liues, though they ſhould receyue nothing for their labour. Doubtleſſe in all our workes wee muſt ſeeke his glorie: and if he beſtow any reward vpon vs, we may take it as an vndeſerued gift of his bountifull goodneſſe. For when wee haue done all that wee can doe, or which is enioyned vpon vs, we muſt confeſſe, that wee are vnprofitable ſeruants.
<note n="x" place="margin">Luke. 17.10.</note>
            </p>
            <p>True it is, that righteous perſons haue ſome hypocriſie and vaine glorie mingled with ſinceritie in their beſt actions, and doe ſome things as wel for their own praiſe, as Gods glory: yet if their ſinceritie preuaile ouer their hypocriſie, they loſe not the name &amp; dignitie of righteous perſons. For as the philoſopher teacheth, concerning elementarie bodies, that they are not made of one element onely, but of all foure, yet haue their names of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dominant element: And as the phyſitions ſay, of the humors in mans body, that although they be not pure, but mixed one with another, yet euery one doth carrie the name of that humor, which doth moſt abound: So may we ſay (and that truely too) of the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall conuerſation and the particular actions of men, that if in them they ſeeke more the glorie of God, then their owne praiſe, pleaſure or profit, they are truely righteous; though imperfectly righteous. The third is by their perſeuerance in righteouſnes. For euery righteous man (who is righteous indeed) will continue in his righteouſnes vnto the end. Hee will not begin onely well, but he wil end alſo wel. He is not like vnto the ſnaile, that puſheth out a long paire of hornes, which being touched neuer ſo little, goe in againe. Neither is his righteouſnes like a morning cloud, or as a morning deaw, which is dryed vp quickly, and vaniſheth away, ſo
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:2851:8"/>ſoone as the Sunne aſcendeth on high. But hee is rather like vnto the tree, that neuer fadeth, but beareth fruite ſtill. And his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes is like to the Iuie, that is alwayes greene, though the Sunne parch it: to the <hi>Diamond,</hi> that is alwayes hard, though the hammer beat it: &amp; to the good vine, that is always growing, thogh the knife cut it. <hi>Whoſoeuer is borne of God</hi> (ſaith <hi>S. Iohn) ſinneth not, for his ſeede remaineth in him: neither can he ſinne, becauſe he is borne of God.</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">1. Ioh. 3.9.</note> And ſurely, true and ſauing righteouſneſſe is one of thoſe gifts of God, which are without repentance.
<note n="y" place="margin">Rom. 11.29.</note> It cannot be loſt fully &amp; finally: <hi>Thoſe which turne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their righteouſnes, &amp; commit iniquitie, ſhall not liue: their former righteouſnes ſhalbe forgotten, and they ſhall dye in their ſinnes, which they haue committed.</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">Ezek. 18.24.</note> He onely, which continueth righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to the end, ſhall be ſaued.
<note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 10.22</note> Wherfore as God neuer ceaſeth to beſtow bleſſings vpon vs, ſo let vs neuer ceaſe to doe ſeruice vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him: for <hi>proemium aeternum, aeternam requirit ſeruitutem:</hi> a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall reward, doth require a continuall ſeruice. Doubtleſſe the Heauens aboue vs, the earth vnder vs, the beaſts about vs, and our people with vs, doe daily crie vpon vs, for the performance of this dutie by vs; for they all ſerue vs euermore, and howſoeuer we doe abuſe them often in their ſeruice, yet they do continue therin ſtill, and neuer giue it ouer. Let this then bee the concluſion of this point, that howſoeuer wee hire ſeruants but for a yeare, and take Apprentices but for ſeuen or eight yeares, yet muſt wee our ſelues ſerue the Lord our God, for all our yeares, and that in holines and righteouſnes, all the dayes of our liues,
<note n="b" place="margin">Luk. 1.17.</note> doing as <hi>Paul</hi> did, when he ſaid, <hi>Brethren, I count not my ſelfe, that I haue attained vnto it, but one thing I doe, I forget that which is behinde, and endeuour my ſelfe vnto that which is before, and follow hard towards the marke, for the price of the high calling of God in Chriſt Ieſus.</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Phil. 3.13.14.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The fourth and laſt is, by their affection to righteouſnes in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. For euery righteous man (who is righteous indeed) will loue righteouſnes as well in others, as in himſelfe: yea, hee will loue all others in whom he beholdeth any ſeeds of righteouſnes. His de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light will be in the Saints, that are on the earth, and in the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, according to <hi>Dauids</hi> example, in theſe words: <hi>My well-doing extendeth not to thee (ô Lord) but to the Saints that are in earth,</hi> and to <hi>the excellent, all my delight is in them.</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> It is well obſerued by the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:2851:8"/>Prophet in the fifteenth pſalme, and the fourth verſe thereof: That thoſe that ſhall dwell in Gods Tabernacle, and reſt in his holy mountaine, doe honour all ſuch as feare the Lord. You know, that he which loueth a childe for his fathers ſake (as <hi>Dauid</hi> loued <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiboſheth,</hi> for <hi>Ionathans</hi> ſake,) loueth the father himſelfe better: So hee which loueth righteouſnes, for righteouſnes ſake, declareth thereby, that hee loueth righteouſnes it ſelfe farre better. Beſides this, a righteous man loueth righteouſnes ſo well, that hee will la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to make others as righteous as himſelfe. <hi>Dauid</hi> promiſed, that if the Lord would create in him a cleane heart, and renew a right ſpirit within him, and ſo referre him to the ioy of his ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: hee would then teach his way vnto the wicked, and vſe means to conuert ſinners vnto him.
<note n="e" place="margin">Pſalm 51.13.</note> And <hi>Peter,</hi> when he is conuerted, muſt ſtrengthen his brethren.
<note n="f" place="margin">Luke 22.32.</note> Doubtleſſe as euery thing ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth to beget his like: ſo a righteous perſon ſeeketh to make an other righteous. And as fire cannot be ſmoothered, when once it hath taken holde in any place, and findeth matter ſufficient to worke vpon, but will burne further and further, till it hath conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med all before it: So true righteouſnes, wrought in the ſoule of one, cannot there bee ſuppreſſed, but will ſpread it ſelfe abroad, and worke vpon others for their conuerſion. In one word then, hee which would be reputed righteous, and yet keepeth in all his righteouſnes to himſelfe, and doth not impart it vnto others, may iuſtly bee ſuſpected to haue little or no ſound righteouſneſſe at all within him.</p>
            <p>Thus farre for the perſon, of whome the Prophet doth ſpeake. Now let vs come to the things, whereof hee doth ſpeake. <hi>The troubles</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>of the righteous are many.</hi> By the word <hi>Troubles,</hi> you muſt vnderſtand, all ſuch things, as doe moleſt or diſquiet him. The Hebrew word is <hi>Ranghoth</hi> in the plurall number,
<note place="margin">Ranghoth.</note> of <hi>Raughah,</hi> in the ſingular. And howſoeuer it be taken now and then, Adiectiuely, for that which is ſinfull or painefull, yet here it is put ſubſtantiuely, and doth note out <hi>Euils,</hi> or afflictions; not euils, as they are ſinnes, but as they are chaſtiſeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts. For euill is of 2. ſorts, the one is <hi>Malum Culpae,</hi> and the other is <hi>malum paenae;</hi> the one the euill of ſinne, the other is the euill of puniſhment. And well may euils or afflictions be called <hi>Troubles,</hi> euen of the effects of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:2851:9"/>them, becauſe they are wont to trouble ſuch as haue them. You ſee now the meaning of the words, the doctrine ariſing from them is this. <hi>That good men and good women ſhall haue troubles heere in this world.</hi> Looke how many will truely feare the Lord, and taking hold of Chriſt Ieſus by a liuely faith, will carefully endeuour to walke in Gods commandements; to the ende of their dayes, they ſhall haue croſſes and troubles, there afflictions &amp; tribulations do belong to them, and they ſhall be ſure to haue their portion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. So much may we gather out of <hi>Eſayes</hi> words, when hee ſaith, <hi>Behold, I and the children</hi> (meaning the true members of Chriſt, that were willing to heare &amp; obey the words of God, wherof he ſpake before) <hi>whome the Lord hath giuen me, are as ſignes and wonders in Iſrael, by the Lord of Hoſt, which dwelleth in mount Sion.</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Eſay, 8.18.</note> So much we may gather out of <hi>Ieremies</hi> words, when hee ſaith, <hi>Heare I pray you, all people, and behold my ſorrow,</hi> (ſpeaking of the church of God vnder his owne perſon) <hi>My <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgines and my young men are gone in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to captiuitie. I called for my Louers but they deceiued mee, my Prieſts and mine elders periſhed in the city, while they ſought their meate to refreſh their ſoules. Behold ô Lord, how I am troubled:my bowels ſwell, mine heart is turned within me, for I am full of heauines, the ſword ſpoyleth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, as death doth at home. They haue heard, that I mourn, but there is none to comfort me; all mine enemies haue heard of my trouble, &amp; are glad, that thou haſt done it.</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Lament. 1.18.19 20 21.</note> So much we may gather out of Zacharies words, when he ſaith, <hi>Ariſe ô ſword vpon my Shepheard, and vpon the man that is my fellow,</hi> ſaith the Lord of Hoaſts, <hi>ſmite the ſhepheard, and the ſheepe ſhalbe ſcattered, &amp; I will turne mine hand vpon the lettle ones. And in all the Land,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>two parts therein ſhall bee cut off, &amp; dye: but the third ſhall be left therein: And I will bring that third part through the fire, and will fine them, as the ſiluer is fined:</hi> and <hi>will trie them, as the gold is tryed. They ſhall call on my Name, and I will heare them: I will ſay, It is my people, and they ſhall ſay, the Lord is my God.</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Zach. 13.7.8.9.</note> So much we may gather out of Chriſts words, when he ſaith: <hi>Behold</hi> (ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to his diſciples) <hi>I ſend you as ſheepe in the mids of wolues. Beware of men, for they will deliuer you vp to the councels: &amp; will ſcourge you in their Synagogues: And the brother ſhall betray the brother to death; and the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Sonne; and the Children ſhall riſe againſt their Parents, and ſhall cauſe them to die. And yee ſhall be hated of all men for my Name.</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Mat. 10.16.17.18.21.22.</note>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:2851:9"/>So much wee may gather out of <hi>Paules</hi> wordes, when hee ſaith, <hi>For wee are made a gazing ſtocke vnto the world, and to the Angels, and to men, vnto this houre, we both hunger and thirſt, and are naked, and are buf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feted, and haue no certaine dwelling place, and labour, working with our own hands: we are reuiled, and yet we bleſſe: wee are perſecuted, and ſuffer it: wee are euill ſpoken of, and we pray: wee are made as the filth of the world,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 4.9.1.</note> the off-ſcowring of all things vnto this time.</hi> So much laſtly may wee gather, (to omit many other places) out of <hi>Dauids</hi> words, when he ſaith, <hi>haue mercy vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> meô Lord for I am i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> trouble, mine eye, my ſoule &amp; my belly, are conſumed with griefe. For my life is waſted with heauineſſe, &amp; my yeares with mourning; my ſtrength faileth for my paines, and my bones are conſumed. I was a reproach among all mine enemies, but especially among my neighbours, and a feare to mine acquaintance, who ſeeing mee in the ſtreete fledde from mee, I am forgotten, as a dead man out of minde. I am like a broken veſſell: for I haue heard the rayling of great men: feare was on euery ſide, while they conſpired together againſt me, and conſulted to take my life.</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Pſalm. 31.9.10.11.</note> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
               </label> But what may the cauſes heereof bee? Is it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are more baſe then others, by their ſtocke and paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage? <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> No: For in that reſpect, they are the honourableſt perſons in all the world: as beeing begotten and borne, not of mortall, but of immortall ſeed, euen of <hi>GOD</hi> himſelfe:
<note n="n" place="margin">Ioh. 1.13.</note> Is it, becauſe they are more wicked then others, by their workes, and wayes? No: for in that reſpect, they are the holieſt perſons in all the world: as beeing waſhed from their ſinnes,
<note n="o" place="margin">Reu. 1.5.</note> and as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing their conuerſation aboue in the heauens themſelues.
<note n="p" place="margin">Phil. 3.20</note> Is it, becauſe they are more deteſtable in the eyes of God then others, by their eſtate and condition? No: for in that reſpect they are the deareſt
<note n="q" place="margin">Prou: 15.9. Acts 10 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5. Ioh. 14.23.</note> perſons vnto him in all the world: as being incorpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into the body of his Sonne, and made his children by adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.
<note n="r" place="margin">Epheſ. 1.4.5.</note> Is it becauſe they are more beggarly then others by their portion of goods and inheritance here below? No: for in that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect they are the richeſt perſons in all the world, if not by profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, yet by right, as beeing the heires of all things; yea, coheyres with Chriſt, of euery thing.
<note n="s" place="margin">Rom. 8.17.</note> So that a man may ſay to them, as <hi>Paul</hi> did to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> in theſe words, <hi>Let no man reioyce in men: for all things are yours: whether it be Paul, or Apollos, or Cephas, or the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:2851:10"/>world, or life, or death, whether they bee things preſent, or things to come, euen all are yours.</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">1. Cor. 3.21.22</note> It is, becauſe they are more troubleſome then others, by their quarrelſome contentions and brawlings? No: for in that reſpect they are the quieteſt perſons in all the world: as turning their ſpeares and ſwords into mattocks and ſythes,
<note n="v" place="margin">Eſal. 2.4.</note> and as going like ſheepe to the ſlaughter-houſe, to bee ſlaine of others themſelues.
<note n="w" place="margin">Rom. 8.36.</note> So that a man may ſay moſt truely, as <hi>Eſay</hi> hath-it in his propheſie, <hi>that in the mount of the Lord, there is no hurt done.</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Eſay. 11.9</note> Is it, becauſe they are more careleſly attended vpon for defence, then others by their place and calling? No: for in that reſpect they are the ſafeſt perſons in all the world: as hauing the Angels of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen aboue them for their guard,
<note n="y" place="margin">Pſalm. 91.11.</note> and the almighty himſelfe for their protection.
<note n="z" place="margin">Palm. 125.2.</note> Is it laſtly, becauſe they are more fruitles then others by their idlenes and want of care to doe men good? No: for in that reſpect they are the profitableſt perſons in all the world: as being full of good workes, and doing good vnto all men.
<note n="a" place="margin">Iob 29.120. Acts. 9.39. Acts, 10.2.</note> So that many doe fare the better for their ſakes. As <hi>Laban</hi> did for <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobs</hi> ſake.
<note n="b" place="margin">Geneſ. 30.27.</note> 
               <hi>Potiphar</hi> for <hi>Ioſephs</hi> ſake:
<note n="c" place="margin">Gen. 39 5.</note> the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> for <hi>Moſes</hi> ſake. <hi>Zoar</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Exod. 32.14.</note> for <hi>Lot</hi> ſake:
<note n="e" place="margin">Gen 19.21.</note> &amp; the marriners for <hi>Pauls</hi> ſake.
<note n="f" place="margin">Acts. 17.24.</note> You ſee then, that it is not for any of theſe cauſes: nay, for theſe cauſes a man may wonder, why they haue any troubles at all: ſeeing thus that they are the honourableſt, the holieſt; to God, the deareſt: in right to all things the richeſt; by a ſweete courage, the quieteſt; through angels protection the ſafeſt; and to men of the world, the profitableſt perſons that are in the world: a wonder I ſay may be made, why they ſhould haue any troubles at all.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>
               </label> But the cauſes are euident, and they are theſe. Firſt, becauſe God in loue will correct them. Secondly, becauſe the diuell in malice will aſſault them. And thidly, becauſe the world in hatred will purſue them. How God in loue will correct them, you may read in the Prouerbs, in the Hebrews, and in the Reuelations. In the prouerbs in theſe words. <hi>My ſonne, refuſe not the chaſtening of the Lord, neither be grieued with his correction, for the Lord correcteth him whom he loueth, euen as the father doth the childe, in whom he delighteth.</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Prou: 3.11.12</note> In the Hebrews in theſe words. <hi>My ſonne, deſpiſe not the chaſtning of the Lord, neither faint, when thou art rebuked of him; for whom the Lord loueth he chaſteneth, and he ſcourgeth euery ſonne that he receiueth.</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:2851:10"/>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Heb. 12.4.6.</note> In the <hi>Reuelations,</hi> in theſe words, <hi>As many as I loue, I rebuke, and chaſten, be zealous therefore and amend.</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Rom. 3.20,</note>
            </p>
            <p>The ende that God doth aime at in correcting his, is alwayes good. In reſpect of them it is twofold. The one is principall: the other is ſubordinate, ſeruing to that principall. The principall, is their ſaluation, according to <hi>Pauls</hi> ſaying, in theſe words: <hi>For this cauſe many are weake, and ſicke among you, and many ſleepe: For if wee would iudge our ſelues, we ſhould not be iudged: but when wee are iudged, we are chaſtned of the Lord, becauſe wee ſhould not be condemned with the world:</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">1. Cor. 11 31.32.</note> The ſubordinate, ſeruing to the principall, is their <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification:</hi> accordingly as wee read in the <hi>Hebrues,</hi> in theſe words. <hi>For they verily</hi> (ſpeaking of the fathers of our bodies) <hi>for a fewe dayes chaſteneth vs after their owne pleaſures; but hee</hi> (ſpeaking of God, the Father of our ſpirits, <hi>chasteneth vs for our profite, that we might be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of his holineſſe.</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Heb: 12.20.</note> In which <hi>Sanctification</hi> of theirs, the Lord hath an eye, eyther to their ſinnes, or to their graces. To their ſinnes, either paſt, that they might repent for them: or preſent, that they might leaue them; or to come, that they might preuent them. To their Graces, eyther for the receiuing of them, that they might be fit to entertaine them: or for the diſcouering of them, that they might appeare to the world: to the praiſe of the giuer, to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of the poſſeſſor; and to the profite of the beholder: or for the exerciſing of them, that they might not ruſt by lying ſtill, like y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron; or grow vnſauorie, like ſtanding-water; but gliſter like golde in the fire, and proſper like the tree by the riuers ſide.</p>
            <p>How the Diuell in malice will aſſault them. You may finde in <hi>Iob,</hi> in <hi>Zacharie,</hi> in <hi>Mathew,</hi> in <hi>Marke,</hi> in <hi>Luke,</hi> in <hi>Paul,</hi> in <hi>Peter,</hi> and in the <hi>Reuelations.</hi> He tormented <hi>Iob,</hi> and ſpared not.
<note n="m" place="margin">Iob. 1. &amp; 2.</note> He ſtood at the right hand of <hi>Iehoſhuah</hi> the high Prieſt to reſiſt him:
<note n="n" place="margin">Zach. 3, 1.</note> Hee tempted Chriſt in the wildernes.
<note n="o" place="margin">Matt. 4.26.</note> Hee ſet vpon the Apoſtles, and winnowed them like wheate.
<note n="p" place="margin">Luke. 22.31.</note> Hee threw a young man of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten into the fire, and into the water, to deſtroy him.
<note n="q" place="margin">Mar. 9.22.</note> Hee buffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Paule,</hi> and was a pricke to him in the fleſh.
<note n="r" place="margin">2. Cor. 1.2.7.</note> Hee caſt out water after the Woman, like a flood to drowne her, and went and made warre with the remnant of her ſeede, which keepe the commandements of God, and haue the teſtimony of Ieſus Chriſt.
<note n="s" place="margin">Reu. 12.15.16.17.</note> Beeing loſed out of his priſon, hee goeth out to deceiue the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:2851:11"/>people which are in the foure quarters of the earth, euen <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> to gather them together to battell againſt the Saints.
<note n="t" place="margin">Rou. 20.8.9.</note> In a word, hee walketh vp and downe, like a roaring lyon, ſeeking daily whom hee may deuour.
<note n="v" place="margin">1. Pet. 5.8.</note>
            </p>
            <p>How laſtly, the world in hatred will purſue them, you may ſee in the Pſalmes: in <hi>Obadiah,</hi> in <hi>Matthew,</hi> in <hi>Iohn,</hi> in <hi>Paul,</hi> and in the <hi>Reuelations.</hi> In the Pſalmes, in theſe wordes, <hi>Thou makeſt vs to turne backe from the aduerſaries, and they which hate vs, ſpoyle for themſelues. Thou giueſt vs as ſheepe to be eaten, and doeſt ſcatter vs among the Nations.</hi>
               <note n="w" place="margin">Pſal. 144.10.11</note> In <hi>Obadiah,</hi> in theſe words: <hi>For thy crueltie againſt thy brother Iacob, ſhame ſhall couer thee, and thou ſhalt be cut off for euer. When thou ſtoodeſt on the other ſide, in the day that the ſtrangers carryed away his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, &amp; ſtrangers entred into his gates, &amp; caſt lottes vpon Ieruſalem, euen thou waſt as one of them.</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Obad. 10.11.</note> In <hi>Mathew,</hi> in theſew words, <hi>Beware of men, for they will deliuer you vp to the councells, &amp; will ſcourge you in their Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues. And the Brother ſhall betray the brother to death, and the Father the Sonne: and the children ſhall riſe againſt theyr parents, and ſhall cauſe them to die. And yee ſhall be hated of all men for my Name.</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">Matt. 10.17.21.22.</note> In <hi>Iohn,</hi> in theſe words, <hi>If you were of the world, the world would loue his owne: but becauſe you are not of the world, but I haue choſen you out of the world, therefore the world hateth you.</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">Ioh. 15.</note> In <hi>Paul,</hi> in theſe words,
<note n="a" place="margin">Gal, 4, 29.</note> 
               <hi>But as then hee that was borne after the fleſh, perſecuted him that was borne after the Spirit.</hi> Euen ſo it is now. Laſtly, in the <hi>Reuelations,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Reu. 20.9.</note> in theſe words, <hi>And they went vp (ſpeaking of Gog and Magog, whom the diuel had gathered together like the ſand of the Sea) into the plaines of the earth, which compaſſed the tents of the Saints about, and the beloued City, but fire came downe from God out of heauen, and deuoured them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> Wherefore trouble is no ſigne of of <hi>reiection,</hi> but rather a marke of <hi>Election.</hi> As the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>If you endure chaſtening, God offereth himſelfe vnto you,
<note n="c" place="margin">Heb. 12.7.8</note> as vnto his ſonnes. For what Sonne is it whom the Father chaſteneth not? If therefore you be without correction, wherof all are par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers, then are you baſtards, and not ſonnes.</hi> To hell a man may ſaile with a forewinde, and meete with fewe or no troubles in his way, but not ſo to heauen.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Iſrael</hi> was going to <hi>Aegipt,</hi> they met no foes: but when they came from <hi>Aegipt</hi> to go to <hi>Chanaan,</hi> they met with many. <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus</hi> had a bitter battell as it were in his way to heauen, when the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:2851:11"/>rich Glutton ſayled ſmoothly to hell, with neuer a rub as it were in his way. Doubtleſſe as the pureſt corne is cleaneſt fanned: the fineſt gold is ofteneſt tried: and the ſweeteſt grape is hardeſt preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: ſo the trueſt Chriſtian is heauieſt croſſed: He is like the Oxe, alwayes held to the plough: but others, who are reprobates, are like the beaſts in a fatte paſture, deſigned to the ſlaughter-houſe. Their iudgement then is erroneous, who brand them with the blacke coale of reprobation: that are ſcorched often with the hote beames of tribulation. Let their credit and authority be as great for wiſedome and for pietie, as euer the credite of <hi>Eliphaz, Bildad,</hi> and <hi>Zophar</hi> was: yet they are to bee cenſured of vs, in this point, and their iudgement to be valued of vs not worth a point, as they and theirs were of God,
<note n="d" place="margin">Iob. 42.7.</note> for condemning <hi>Iob</hi> for his troubles, who was a man more excellent then themſelues, and
<note n="e" place="margin">Iob. 42.8.</note> dearer vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Almightie, then any of them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, out of this we may learne, not to bee aſhamed of all ſuch, as are heere in this world, in troubles, and afflictions, ſeeing good men and good women are ſubiect therevnto; but rather to make much of ſuch, and to regard them aboue others; as wee are aduiſed for to doe, both by precept, and by patterne. By precept,
<note n="f" place="margin">Heb. 2, 13, 3.</note> in the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> in theſe words; <hi>Remember them that are in bonds, as though you were bound with them, and them that are in affliction, as if you were alſo afflicted in the body.</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Heb: 10.32, 33 34</note> By pattern, in the ſame book, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſaith, <hi>Now call to remembrance the dayes that are paſſed, in the which, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter you had receiued light, you endured a great fight in afflictions, partly while you were made a gazing ſtocke, both by reproches and afflictions, and partly, while you became companions of them which were ſo toſſed too &amp; fro. For both you ſorrowed with mee for my bonds, and ſuffered with ioy the ſpoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of your goods, knowing in your ſolues, how that you haue in heauen a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and an enduring ſubſtance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, from hence wee may ſee, that righteous perſons doe ſtand in neede of helpe and fauour from others, conſidering thus, that their eſtate is full of troubles: Prayers are to bee made vnto God for them, as they were for <hi>Peter,</hi> when hee was in priſon.
<note n="h" place="margin">Acts, 12.5</note> Money is to be conferred vpon them, as it was vpon the brethren in <hi>Iudea,</hi> when there was a great famine amongſt them, in the dayes of <hi>Claudius Caſar.</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Acts 11, 99.</note> Comfort muſt be miniſtred vnto them, as it
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:2851:12"/>was vnto the inceſtuous <hi>Corinthian,</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was deiected with too much ſorrow for his ſinne.
<note n="k" place="margin">2. Cor. 2.7.</note> Laſtly, heauenly exhortatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s muſt be made amongſt them, as they were amongſt the Saints of <hi>Lyſtra, I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conms,</hi> and <hi>Antiochia,</hi> when <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> came to confirme, and to exhort them to continue in the faith.
<note n="l" place="margin">Acts 14.22.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Finally, out of this place wee gather, that looke how many of vs, as doe intend to be righteous, wee muſt prepare our hearts for troubles, and not be diſmaide at the ſame, when they fall vpon vs; as though ſome ſtrange thing did happen vnto vs, according to <hi>Peters</hi> words, when he ſaith; <hi>Deerly beloued, thinke it not ſtrange con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the fierie triall, which is among you to proue you, as though ſome ſtrange things were come vnto you; but reioyce, in aſmuch as you are par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of Christs ſufferings, that when his glorie ſhall appeare, you may be glad and reioyce.</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">1. Pet. 4.12.13.</note> Wherefore my beloued brethren, prepare your hearts for troubles, and looke for them euery day. Behold, as wee muſt prepare for warre, when wee heare of the comming of our enemies: and as wee muſt prepare for a ſhelter, when wee ſee the comming of a ſtorme. Like as <hi>Noah</hi> prepared an Arke againſt the comming of the flood. So in wiſedome muſt we prepare for the comming of our troubles, that ſo when they doe come, they may either not trouble vs at all, or elſe trouble vs but a little. Now the meanes of preparation ſtandeth chiefly in the meditation of three points. The firſt is of the neceſſitie of troubles, how they will and muſt come, doe man what he can to the contrary: As our Sauiour ſaid to <hi>Peter, When thou waſt young, thou girdedſt thy ſelfe, and walkedſt whither thou wouldeſt, but whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou ſhalt be old, thou ſhalt ſtretch forth thine hands, and an other ſhall guide thee, and leade thee whither thou wouldest not.</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Ioh, 11.18</note> For <hi>praemonitus, praemunitus,</hi> hee that is fore-warnde, is fore-armde: afflictions are lightned in the expectation. Hereof was it, that Chriſt did foretell his diſciples, how they ſhould be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained heere in this world:
<note n="o" place="margin">Mat. 10, 16.17</note> and did ſhewe <hi>Paul</hi> how many things he was to ſuffer for his Names
<note n="p" place="margin">Acts. 9.16</note> ſake.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is, of the vtilitie of troubles, how they will bring great profite to them who are exerciſed therewith. And theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites are chiefly foure: whereof two doe concerne this life, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther two the next life. Thoſe two which doe concerne this life, are holineſſe &amp; credit. Holines is wrought in man by afflictions,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:2851:12"/>as we may read in the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> in theſe words: <hi>For they verily for a few dayes chaſtened vs after their owne pleaſures, but he chaſteneth vs for our profite, that wee might be partakers of his holineſſe:
<note n="q" place="margin">Heb. 12.10.11.</note> Now no chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing for the preſent ſeemeth to be ioyous, but grieuous: but afterwards it bringeth the quiet fruit of righteouſnes, vnto them which are thereby exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed.</hi> It is an olde ſaying, and a true one, <hi>Crux pendentis, Cathedra docentis:</hi> the croſſe of the hanged, is the chaire of the learned. The Croſſe-houſe is the Schoole-houſe.</p>
            <p>Surely Afflictions as they are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; ſo are they alſo <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; as they are paſſions, ſo they are inſtructions: they are not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly burdens vpon vs, but they are alſo good leſſons vnto vs: They are like the winde, which doth cleanſe the good graine, though it doth blow colde: and like the Fire, which doth purifie the bad golde, though it doth burne hote. <hi>Hagar</hi> was proud and blinde in <hi>Abrahams</hi> houſe, but in the wildernes ſhee is humbled, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins to looke to the Lord.
<note n="r" place="margin">Geneſ. 16.4.</note> 
               <hi>Iſrael</hi> learned not to mourne, vntill they were ſent to <hi>Babell.
<note n="s" place="margin">Pſalm. 137.10.</note> Ionah</hi> ſleepe in the ſhippe, but walkes and prayes in the whales belly.
<note n="t" place="margin">Iona. 1. &amp; 2. chapt.</note> 
               <hi>Manaſſes</hi> cares not for God at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, but ſeekes him out in the priſon.
<note n="v" place="margin">2. Cron. 33.12</note> 
               <hi>Dauid</hi> went aſtray be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was afflicted, but then he learned to keepe Gods word.
<note n="w" place="margin">Pſalm, 119.67</note> In a word, euery Chriſtian is bettered by his troubles. His know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is ſounder then it was: His faith is ſtronger then it was: his hope is firmer then it was: his loue is hotter then it was: his humilitie is lower then it was: laſtly, his goodneſſe in generall, is greater then it was: greater towards God, greater towards his neighbour, greater towards himſelfe, and greater towards all the creatures both great and ſmall.</p>
            <p>As thus wee haue holineſſe by afflictions, ſo alſo haue we cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto you it is grace: For Christ</hi> (ſaith Paul,) <hi>that not onely you ſhould belieue in him, but alſo ſuffer for his ſake.</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Phil: 1.29.</note> In the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond chapter of the <hi>Reuelation,</hi> and 13. verſe, it is recorded as a thing of great honor, that <hi>Antipas</hi> was ſlaine, as a faithfull martyr, in the Church of <hi>Pergamus,</hi> where Sathan had his throne. And the Apoſtles did take themſelues highly credited of the Lord, when he did count them worthy to ſuffer for his Names ſake.
<note n="z" place="margin">Acts 5.41.</note> So that honour and reputation comes to men by all ſuch afflictions as they doe vndergo here in this world for Gods cauſe, and the confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:2851:13"/>of the truth. The other two profits, which doth concerne the next life, are theſe. Firſt, an aſſurance of glorie to come. For this is certaine; that if wee doe here ſuffer with Chriſt, wee ſhall heereafter raigne with Chriſt.
<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 8.17. 2. Tim. 2.13. 1. Pet. 3.10.</note> And therefore <hi>Iames</hi> doth ſay, <hi>Bleſſed is the man that endureth temptation: for when he is tryed, he ſhall receiue the crowne of life, which the Lord hath promiſed to them that loue him.</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Iam 1.12.</note> Secondly, an increaſe of glorie to come. For (as <hi>Paul</hi> doth teach vs) <hi>our light affliction, which is but for a moment, cauſeth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs a farre more excellent and an eternall weight of glorie.</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">2. Cor. 4.17.</note> So that the more troubles that wee doe here endure for our God and his lawes, the more and greater will our glory be at the laſt, when we ſhall be rewarded according to our workes.
<note n="d" place="margin">2. Cor. 5.10.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The third and laſt meanes of preparation for troubles, is the conſideration of the multiplicitie of thoſe promiſes which God hath made vnto vs in his word, about our troubles, which promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes are chiefly three. The firſt is, that hee will lay no more vpon vs then wee can beare: according to <hi>Pauls</hi> words, when hee ſaith, <hi>There hath no temptation taken you, but ſuch as appertaineth to man: and God is faithfull, which will not ſuffer you to bee tempted aboue that you be able, but will giue the iſſue with the temptation, that you may bee able to beare it.</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">1. Cor. 10.13.</note> The ſecond is, that he will deliuer vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that which he doth lay vpon vs, according to <hi>Dauids</hi> words; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſaith, <hi>As the mountains are about Ieruſalem, ſo is the Lord about his people, from hence forth, and for euer. For the rod of the wicked ſhall not reſt on the lot of the righteous, leaſt the righteous put forth their hand vnto wickednes.</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Pſal. 125.2.3.</note> The third and laſt is, that hee will turne that which he doth lay vpon vs, and from which he will deliuer vs, vnto our good in the ende: according to the Apoſtles words, when he ſaith, <hi>Alſo we knowe that all things worke together for the beſt vnto them that loue God, euen to them that are called of his purpoſe.</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Rom. 8.28.</note> Thus by the contemplation of the neceſſitie of troubles, of the vtilitie of troubles, and of the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitie of the promiſes, which God hath made vnto vs about our troubles; you may make your ſelues ſtrong, and prepare your hearts againſt all your troubles. And ſo I leaue the firſt branch of the miſerie of the righteous, which doth concerne the nature or qualitie of it, and come to the ſecond, which dooth reſpect the magnitude or quantitie of it.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:2851:13"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Many are the troubles</hi> (ſaith the Prophet) <hi>of the Righteous.</hi> The word which is here tranſlated <hi>Many,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rabboth.</note>in the <hi>Hebrew</hi> tongue is <hi>Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both,</hi> and it coms of the verb <hi>Rabab,</hi> with ſignifieth to multiplie or to increaſe. Some there are, who read it thus, <hi>Great are the troubles of the righteous.</hi> True it is, that the word <hi>Rab</hi> and <hi>Rabbah,</hi> whereof come <hi>Rabin</hi> and <hi>Rabboth</hi> in the plurall, doe ſignifie now and then that which is great: but yet you muſt know, that it is but ſeldome, and that for the moſt part it is taken onely for that which is much, or many, and ſo is it here. For the Prophets meaning is, that there is a generalitie of croſſes, and a plurality of troubles, that doe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the righteous. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> Where hence ariſeth this doctrine, that the afflictions or calamities, wherevnto the children of God are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, are many and diuerſe. Many and diuerſe, 1. for the perſons, from whome they come. 2. For the meanes through which they come. 3. For the times wherein they come. 4. For the ſortes by which they come. 5. For the ports to which they come. 6. Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for the effects which they bring at their comming. The per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons from whom troubles doe come, are many and diuerſe. Firſt and foremoſt, there is <hi>GOD</hi> the Father, the Sonne &amp; holy Ghoſt. Secondly, there is the diuell and his angells. Thirdly, there is the world, and all vngodly perſons who are in the world, that are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt infinite in number, beeing as the ſand of the Sea.
<note n="h" place="margin">Reu. 20.8.</note> The meanes through which troubles doe come, are many and diuerſe: For they come ſometimes through the meanes of our Children: ſomtimes through the meanes of our ſeruants: ſomtimes through the meanes of our friends: ſometimes through the meanes of our enemies: ſometimes through the meanes of our Neighbours: ſomtimes through the meanes of ſtrangers: and ſomtimes laſtly, (to omit many other meanes,) through the meanes of our owne fooliſh or ſinfull wayes. The times wherein troubles doe come, are many and diuerſe. For ſometimes they come in the morning, ſometimes at noone, ſometimes in the euening, and ſometimes in the night: Sometimes in our infancie, ſomtimes in our childhood, ſometimes in our youth, ſometimes in our middle-age, ſometimes in our olde-age, ſometimes in our dotage. The ſorts by which troubles do come, are many and diuerſe. For ſome are the diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the bodie, as the goute, the ſtone, the collicke, the ague, the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:2851:14"/>feauer, the toothach, and the like.</p>
            <p>Some are wants of outward things, as of houſes, Cattell, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, Apparell, Dyet, Friends, libertie, and the like. Some are loſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of goods; as when a man is robbed of his money, of his plate, of his clothes, of his beaſts, of his ſeruants, of his children, and the like. Some laſtly (to paſſe ouer other ſorts) are the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon plagues of the world; as burnings by the fire, as drownings by the water, as infectings by the aire, as deuourings by the Sword, as deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings by the peſtilence, as ſlanderings by the tongue, and the like. The parts to which troubles doe come are many and diuerſe. For ſomtimes they come vnto the ſoule, &amp; ſomtimes to the bodie, and ſometimes both to the ſoule and body together. Likewiſe in the bodie, they come now and then vnto the head: now and then to the bellie: now and then to the backe: now and then to the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack: now &amp; then to the arms: now and then to the thighs: now and then to the legs: now &amp; then to the feete: now &amp; then to the hands: and now &amp; then in a word, to all the ioynts and members of the body together. The effects which troubles do bring forth at their comming, are many and diuerſe. For ſomtimes they make men mery, and ſometimes againe they make them ſad: ſometimes they make them pray; &amp; ſometimes againe they make them curſe: ſometimes they make them quiet, and ſomtimes againe they make them rage: ſomtimes in a word they make them the worſe, &amp; ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times again they make them the better. Thus the troubles of the righteous are many. <hi>Innumerable troubles</hi> (ſaith <hi>Dauid) haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſed me.</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Pſalm. 40.12.</note> The Church doth thus complain: <hi>They haue oftentimes afflicted mee from my youth, (may Iſrael now ſay) they haue oftentimes afflicted mee from my youth, but they could not preuaile againſt mee. The plowers plowed vpon my backe, and made long ſurrowes.</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Pſalm. 129.1.2.3.</note> And <hi>wee muſt</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas) through many afflictions enter into the kingdome of God.</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Acts 14.22.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; through many compreſſions or twiſtings to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether of the Greeke word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> doth import. For this cauſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions are compared to waters, becauſe as one waue falleth vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on another, ſo one trouble commeth after another.
<note n="m" place="margin">Pſalm. 42.7.</note> I might make this more manifeſt vnto you, by manifolde examples out of Gods word: as by the example of <hi>Iacob,</hi> of <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> of <hi>Iob,</hi> &amp; others: but at this inſtant I will giue you inſtance only in two: namely, in <hi>Dauid</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> wherof the one is in the old Teſtament, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:2851:14"/>in the new.
<note n="n" place="margin">1. Sam. 17.34.</note> A lyon (you know) came to <hi>Dauid</hi> to deuoure him: a beare to teare him:
<note n="o" place="margin">1. Sam. 17.41.</note> a giant to kill him:
<note n="p" place="margin">1. Sam. 20. &amp; 21.</note> a king to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head him:
<note n="q" place="margin">2. ſam. 15.12.</note> a ſonne to vnthroan him:
<note n="r" place="margin">2. ſam. 20.10</note> a ſubiect to reiect him: &amp; many
<note n="s" place="margin">2. ſam. 8.10.</note> out-la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>diſh princes to captiue or conquer him. Theſe were troubles, yea many troubles, but yet they were not all. For beſides theſe, you may reade, how his wiues were taken by the enemies, like priſoners;
<note n="t" place="margin">1. ſam. 30.5.</note> how his concubines were defloured openly like whores:
<note n="v" place="margin">2. ſam. 16.22.</note> how his children were defiled with inceſt and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, like pagans:
<note n="w" place="margin">2. ſam. 13.14.32.</note> how his ſubiects were deſtroyed with peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and famine, like beaſts:
<note n="x" place="margin">2. ſam. 21.1.24.15.</note> how his ſouldiers were vp in a mutinie for to ſtone him, like rebells:
<note n="y" place="margin">1. ſam. 30.</note> how his friends were in a confederacie againſt him, like traitors:
<note n="z" place="margin">Pſalm. 41.9. &amp; 55.12.</note> laſtly, how hee him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe was ſtrangely handled both in body and ſoule, by God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, like a caſt-away.
<note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 38.2. and 32.4.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But to leaue him, and to come to <hi>Paul,</hi> in the 2. Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> and 11. chapter, you may plainely ſee how manie his troubles were, by his owne report, who knew them beſt. He had many labors &amp; many ſtripes. He was often in priſon: he was neere vnto death many times. Of the <hi>Iews</hi> he receiued 5. times 40. ſtripes ſauing one. He ſuffered ſhipwrack 3. times. Night and day was he in the deepe Sea. In iournying he was often in perill of waters, in perill of robbers, in perill of his owne nation, in perill among the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> in perils in the citie, in perils in the wildernes, in perill in the ſea, in perils among falſe brethren. In wearines and painfulnes, in warchings often, in hunger &amp; thirſt, in faſtings often, in cold and nakednes. Beſides the things which are outward, he was cumbred daily, and had the care of all churches. So that this is a cleere doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, that the troubles wherevnto the children of God are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, are many and diuerſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>
               </label> Now the reaſons thereof are theſe. Firſt, becauſe they haue many ſinnes. For ſinne is the generall and vniuerſall cauſe of all troubles. <hi>Man ſuffereth for his ſinne</hi> (ſaith <hi>Ieremy</hi>) in the <hi>Lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations.</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Lam. 39.3.</note> And <hi>fooles</hi> (ſaith <hi>Dauid) by reaſon of their tranſgreſſions, and becauſe of their iniquities are afflicted.</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 107.17.</note> You may ſee more of this at your leiſure, in <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 40.12. in <hi>Eſai.</hi> 57.17. in <hi>Lament.</hi> 1.22. and <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.14. God doth knowe that we are like dogges, who ſo long as they are hungry, they faſten their eyes vpon their maiſter,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:2851:15"/>but he no ſooner caſteth downe a cruſt or a bone, but they looke downward, &amp; run after it, little regarding him who feedeth them.</p>
            <p>So is it with vs, ſo long as wee are kept vnder, wee looke vnto the Lord our maiſter, and haue a reſpect to his commandements: but when we are full, and laden with fatneſſe, we ſpurne with the heele, and regard not the ſtrong <hi>GOD</hi> of our ſaluation.
<note n="d" place="margin">Deut. 32.15.</note> For this cauſe doth the Lord oftentimes ſend a deluge vpon the face of our earthly pleaſures, and throwe vs downe into the floods of teares: that ſo thereby hee might extinguiſh the heate of vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full deſires within vs, &amp; clenſe the corruptions of our ſinfull liues, and all to this ende, that wee might not be condemned with the world, but might be ſaued at the day of iudgement: as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle doth well obſerue in his epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> according to that which was quoted before, the firſt Epiſtle, the 11. chapter, and the latter ende of the ſame.</p>
            <p>Secondly, becauſe they haue many enemies. For all the world doth hate them, and the diuell and his power is wholly bent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, and ſo they will alwayes be working one miſchiefe or other, to ouerthrow them. Satan will neuer be quiet, but hee is compaſſing the earth too &amp; fro at all times,
<note n="e" place="margin">Iob. 1.7.</note> and goes about like a roaring lyon ſeeking euermore whom he may deuoure.
<note n="f" place="margin">1. Pet: 5.8.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, becauſe they haue many graces. For as God doth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow more heauenly gifts vpon them, then vpon all the world be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides: ſo he will haue theſe gifts of theirs to be tryed, and made knowne vnto others, for the praiſe of his own Maieſtie who gaue them. They muſt bee beaten like ſpice in the morter, that they may ſmell the better all abroad. <hi>Paul</hi> muſt haue the bufferings of Satan to continue with him ſtill, becauſe hee had grace ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to beare the ſame. <hi>My grace</hi> (ſaith God vnto him) <hi>is ſufficient for thee.</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">2. Cor. 12.9.</note> Surely in this reſpect he dealeth with vs, as we are wont to do with our children. The ſtronger they be, the more and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyer burdens doe we lay vpon them: but the weaker, the fewer, and the lighter. The more able that we be to vndergoe troubles, the more will the Lord exerciſe vs with troubles, but the feebler that we be to beare them, the fewer ſhall we haue.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, becauſe they haue many bleſſings. For the more fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours that they doe receiue from the Almighty, the more are they
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:2851:15"/>ſpited at here in this wretched world: and the more doe the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked oppoſe and ſet themſelues againſt them, to their vtter ruine and ouerthrowe, if it may be. Becauſe the Lord had reſpect vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Habel</hi> and to his offering, but vnto <hi>Cain</hi> and his offering, he had no regard. <hi>Cain</hi> was exceeding wroth, and his countenance fell downe, and afterwards hee roſe vp againſt <hi>Habel</hi> his brother, and ſlewe him.
<note n="h" place="margin">Geneſ. 4.4.5.8</note> In like manner, becauſe <hi>Iſaac</hi> waxed mightie, and ſtill increaſed, till he was exceeding great: (for hee had flocks of ſheepe, and heards of Cattell, and a mightie houſhold,) therefore the <hi>Philiſtims</hi> had enuie at him: inſomuch that the <hi>Philiſtims</hi> ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped and filled vp with earth, all the wells which his Fathers ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants digged in his Father <hi>Abrahams</hi> time. And <hi>Abimelech</hi> the King alſo ſaid vnto him, <hi>Get thee from vs, for thou art mightyer then wee a great deale.</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Geneſ. 26.13.14.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Fiftly, becauſe they haue many exerciſes of holy religion. For as <hi>Daniel</hi> was troubled and caſt into the lyons denne, becauſe he did pray vnto the Lord his God, contrary to the edict of the king.
<note n="k" place="margin">Dan. 6.10.</note> And as the Apoſtles were apprehended and throwne into pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, becauſe they did preach in the Name of Chriſt, contrary to the charge of their gouernours, the high-prieſts, and others,
<note n="l" place="margin">Acts 5, 18.</note> So all thoſe that ſhall bee bowed at any time, in the practiſe of holie duties, and be earneſt and feruent in ſetting forward the exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of true religion, they ſhalbe ſure to be aſſaulted with manifold troubles here amongſt the ſonnes of men.</p>
            <p>Finally, becauſe they haue many contentions in the world a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſinne for righteouſnes, and againſt the diuell for their God. For as the word of God is in their hearts like a burning fire, ſhut vp in their bones, which doe make them weary with forbearing, and vnable for to ſtay.
<note n="m" place="margin">Ier. 20.9.</note> And as they doe teſtifie of the world, that the workes thereof are euill.
<note n="n" place="margin">Iob. 7.7.</note> So the world and the diuell doe rage the more againſt them for the ſame. All were quickly vp in a tumult againſt <hi>Paul,</hi> when he ſpake againſt their idolatry, and by name condemned their goddes <hi>Diana.</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Acts. 19.25.</note> The <hi>Iewes</hi> could not holde when <hi>Stephen</hi> layd to their charge their great impietie, but their harts braſt for anger, and they gnaſhed at him with their teeth: yea, they gaue a ſhowte with a loud voyce, and ſtopped their eares, and ran vpon him all at once, and caſt him out of the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:2851:16"/>and ſtoned him.
<note n="p" place="margin">Acts. 7.54.</note> And howſoeuer <hi>Herod</hi> did reuerence <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptist,</hi> and heard him gladly, yet at the laſt hee did impriſon him, and cauſed his head to be cut off, becauſe hee told him of his faults, and ſaid vnto him; <hi>It is not lawfull for thee to haue thy bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wife.</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Mar. 6.18.</note> Thus you ſee the reaſons why the troubles of the righteous are many. It is becauſe their ſinnes are many. It is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their enemies are many. It is becauſe their graces are many. It is becauſe their bleſſings are many. It is, becauſe their exerciſes of religion are many. It is laſtly, becauſe their contentions againſt the world, the fleſh, and the diuell are many.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>
               </label> The conſideration wherof is profitable vnto vs many waies. For firſt it may ſerue to comfort all ſuch as haue manifold afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and troubles here. They muſt not thinke the worſe of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues for the ſame, but rather the better. For the beſt of all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly are moſt troubled, as we may ſee by the example of the Patriarchs, of the Prophets, of the Apoſtles, of the Euangeliſts, of the martyrs, yea of Chriſt himſelfe, who was to be deſpiſed, and to endure the ſhame of the croſſe, before he could be glorified.
<note n="r" place="margin">Heb: 12.2.</note> And therefore let vs remember what our Sauiour doth ſay of this matter in the Goſpel according to <hi>Saint Matthew,</hi> in theſe words. <hi>Bleſſed are you,</hi> (ſpeaking to his diſciples) <hi>when men reuile you, and perſecute you, and ſay all manner of euill againſt you for myſake falſely. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce &amp; be glad, for great is your reward in heauen; for ſo perſecuted they the Prophets which were before you.</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Matt. 5.11.12.</note> And let vs alſo often thinke vpon that which <hi>Iames</hi> hath in his <hi>Epiſtle,</hi> when he ſaith; <hi>My bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, count it exceeding ioy, when you fall into diuers temptations, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the trying of your faith bringeth foorth patience; and let patience haue her
<note n="t" place="margin">Iam. 1.2.3.4.</note> perfect worke, that you may be perfect and entire lacking nothing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob: </seg>
               </label> But here it may be obiected, that a man may haue many trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and yet be the child of the diuell, according to Dauids ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>Many ſorrowes ſhall come to the wicked.</hi>
               <note n="v" place="margin">Pſalm. 32.10.</note> And according to that which is recorded in the <hi>Reuelation,</hi> in theſe words: <hi>And the fourth Angell powred out his viall on the Sunne, &amp; it was giuen vnto him to torment men with heate of fire, and men boyled in great heate, and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemed the name of God, which hath power ouer theſe plagues: and they repented not to giue him glory: And the fift Angell powred out his viall vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:2851:16"/>on the throane of the beaſt, and his kingdome waxed darke, and they gnew their tongue with ſorrow, &amp; blasphemed the God of heauen, for their paines and for their ſores, and repented not of their works.</hi>
               <note n="w" place="margin">Re. 16.8.9.10</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">An: </seg>
               </label> It is true, but to make a difference, you muſt conſider three re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markeable points. The firſt is, the cauſe of their troubles. For the old ſaying is, <hi>Non poena, ſed cauſa facit martyrem:</hi> It is not the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, but the cauſe that doth make a martyr. Some are like to <hi>Iſmaell,</hi> of whom it is ſaide, <hi>He ſhall be a wilde man; his hand ſhall be againſt euery man, &amp; euery mans hand against him.</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Gene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 16.12</note> Becauſe they trouble others, therfore they haue many troubles themſelues. But if any be railed vpon for the Name of Chriſt, they are bleſſed: and all thoſe who ſuffer, not as a murtherer, nor as a thiefe, nor as an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill dooer, nor as a buſie-body, in other mens matters, but as a Chriſtian, they are happy, &amp; need not to be aſhamed, but may glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie God in that behalfe.
<note n="y" place="margin">1. Pet. 4.14.15.16.</note> The ſecond, is the manner of bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their troubles. For righteous perſons doe quietly vndergoe the ſame, and bleſſe the Lord their God in the midſt thereof, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with olde <hi>Ely, It is the Lord, let him doe what ſeemeth him good:
<note n="z" place="margin">1. ſam. 3.18.</note> With valiant</hi> Dauid, <hi>carry the Arke of GOD againe into the Citie, if I ſhall finde fauour in the eyes of the Lord, he will bring me againe, and ſhew mee both it, and the tabernacle thereof. But if he thus ſay, I haue no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in thee, behold, here am I: Let him do to me as ſeemeth good in his eyes.</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">2. ſam. 15.25.26.</note> And with patient <hi>Iob; Naked came I out of my mothers wombe, and naked ſhall I returne againe: the Lord hath giuen, and the Lord hath taken it: bleſſed bee the Name of the LORD.</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Iob. 1.21.</note> But vngodly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons doe breake out exceedingly, and not onely ſeeke vnlawfull meanes to helpe themſelues in their troubles: as <hi>Saul</hi> reſorted to the witch of <hi>Endor,</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">1. Cor. 10.13.</note> and many enquire at them that haue a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of diuination, and at the Sooth-ſayers, which whiſper end mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mure, forſaking the liuing, to goe to the dead, and the Creator, to goe to the creature:
<note n="d" place="margin">Eſay. 8.19.</note> But they alſo ſtorme and rage now and then like mad-men, and withdrawe all their truſt from the Lord the fountaine of all happineſſe, not praying vnto his Maieſtie for ſuccour and helpe, but rather blaſpheming his glorious name, with their leaud &amp; wicked tongues; as was obſerued a little before out of the <hi>Reuelations.</hi> The third and laſt is the ende, what fruit doth follow: vpon their troubles. For the godly are bettered by them,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:2851:17"/>but the wicked are not. <hi>Dauid</hi> &amp; other righteous men receiued goodnes from them, as was proued before: but <hi>Saul</hi> and other vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly wretches remaine ſtill in their ſinfulnes notwithſtanding them; yea by them they grow worſe and worſe, according to <hi>Pauls</hi> words, when he ſaith; <hi>Yea, and all that will liue godly in Chriſt Ieſus ſhall ſuffer perſecution. But the euill men and deceiuers ſhall waxe worſe and worſe, deceiuing, and being deceiued.</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Mi. 27.3.12.13.</note> Whereunto agreeth that which the prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> hath in theſe words; <hi>they haue forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the Lord, they haue prouoked the holy one of Iſrael to anger, they are gone backward. Wherefore ſhould you be ſmitten any more? for you fall away more and more, the whole head is ſicke, and the whole heart is heauy.</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Eſay. 1.4.5.</note> Now to conclude this point, if the cauſe be holy for which you ſuffer, if it be for God and a good conſcience, and not for your owne defaults or fooliſhnes: if ſecondly, you take your troubles quietly, and poſſeſſe your ſoules with patience in the midſt thereof, relying onely vpon God, and vſing no vnlawfull meanes for your helpe therein: if laſtly you be amended and made better by ſuch chaſtiſements as are laid vpon you, ſo that now you doe become more deuout and religious in the whole courſe of your liues then euer you were before, you may aſſure your ſoules that your caſe is good, and thinke the better of your ſelues for theſe your troubles, and not the worſe. They muſt be ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny pledges and ſeales to you of your euerlaſting happines.</p>
            <p>Secondly, ſeeing the troubles of the righteous are many, righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous perſons haue neede of great patience, a little part or porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on therof will not ſerue their turnes. And therefore let all thoſe who intend to be righteous indeede, endeuour to the vttermoſt of their power, to attaine to a good meaſure of patience, which is like a priuy coate vpon the ſoule to ſaue it; a marble pillar in the houſe to vphold it; a ſtrong poſt vnder the tree to ſtay it: a preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous balme about the head to heale it: and a two edged ſword in the hand to defend it. Doubtles <hi>Sampſon</hi> neuer gained ſo much by his haire vpon his head (and yet when his haire was on his head he did alwaies ouercome, and was neuer ouercome) as we ſhall gaine by patience to helpe vs in all our troubles. For this will be a generall ſalue to vs for all our ſores, and as the lid about the eye is made to ſhut and open to ſaue the eye, ſo this is placed in our
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:2851:17"/>ſoules by the Lord, to guard and keepe our ſoules. For as a light burden borne at the armes end, weigheth heauier by much, then a burden of treble weight, if it be borne vpon the ſhoulders, which are made to beare. So if a man ſet impatience to beare his croſſe, which is not fit to beare, it will ſtart and ſhrinke, and let the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den fall on his head, like a broken ſtaffe, which promiſeth to helpe him ouer the water, and leaueth him in the ditch. But if you put it to patience, and ſet her to beare it, which is appointed to beare, ſhe will vndergoe it, and carry it away as nothing. For ſhe is like the harty ſpies, that came from <hi>Canaan,</hi> and ſaide; <hi>Surely, the Lord hath deliuered into our hands all the land, for euen all the inhabitants of the countrey, faint becauſe of vs.</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Ioſhua. 2.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Or like to <hi>Caleb,</hi> that ſtilled the people before <hi>Moſes,</hi> and ſaid, <hi>Let vs goe vp at once, &amp; poſſeſſe it. For vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly we ſhall ouercome it.</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Numb. 13.31</note> So patience doth euermore hart vs on a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all troubles that may bee, and perſwade our hearts that wee ſhall ouercome them well enough in the end. She doth tell vs, that it is nothing to faſt, nothing to watch, nothing to read, nothing to labour, nothing to be enuied, nothing to be ſlandered, nothing to be buffeted, nothing to bee impriſoned, nothing in a word to be racked, or to be put to death for the Lords cauſe. Shee doth aſſure vs, that we ſhalbe more then conquerorstherin, according to <hi>Pauls</hi> words, in his epiſtle to the <hi>Romanes,</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Rom. 8.37.</note> Labour then I beſeech you for patience, and follow the Apoſtles counſell in this repect, when he ſaith: <hi>Be patient therefore brethren vnto the comming of the Lord; Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the husbandman waiteth for the pretious fruites of the earth, and hath long patience for it, vntill hee receiue the former and latter raine. Be yee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo patient therefore, &amp; ſettle your harts, for the comming of the Lord draws neere.</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Iam. 5.7.8.</note> And ſurely, he that wanteth it, is like a man that ſtandeth trembling in the field without his Armour, becauſe euery one can ſtrike him, and he can ſtrike none againe. The leaſt puſh that is, of diſgrace, or of loſſe, or of ſicknes, or of pouerty, or of paine, doth trouble thoſe perſons more, which haue not patience to beare the ſame, then forty tryalls can moue ſuch as are armed with patience to vndergoe them, like a golden ſhield in their hand, to breake the ſtroke of euery croſſe, and to ſaue the heart, though the bodie ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer. For while the heart is whole, all is well. <hi>A ſound ſpirit</hi> (ſaith <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon) will beare his infirmity, but a wounded ſpirit, who can ſuſtaine it?</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Prou. 18.44.</note>
            </p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:2851:18"/>
            <p>Laſtly, conſidering the afflictions of the godly are many, we that are godly, muſt neuer promiſe to our ſelues peace &amp; quietnes here, but after one trouble, we muſt ſtill looke for another; ſaying with the Poet, <hi>Finis alterius m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>li. gradus eſt futuri:</hi> the end of one euill, is a ſtep towards another. Many do deceiue themſelues with vaine hopes in this reſpect. They thinke that all ſhalbe well with them, that they ſhal haue the Sunne euermore to ſhine vpon them, if they can but rid themſelues out of their preſent troubles. But let them marke it well, it ſhall not be ſo; oh my brethren, ſuppoſe you were as wiſe as <hi>Salomon;</hi> as ſtrong as <hi>Sampſon;</hi> as warlike as <hi>Dauid;</hi> as meeke as <hi>Moſes;</hi> as louely as <hi>Ionathan;</hi> as beautifull as <hi>Abſalom;</hi> as rich as <hi>Croeſſus;</hi> as great as <hi>Aſſuerus;</hi> as ſwift as <hi>Aſahel;</hi> as free born as <hi>Paul;</hi> as noble as <hi>Foeſtus;</hi> as big as <hi>Goliah;</hi> as patient as <hi>Ioh;</hi> and as wiſe as Chriſt himſelfe: yet you ſhall haue troubles ſtill during your liues, ſo long as any of you ſhall breath with any life. As the life of <hi>Christ</hi> your Lord and maiſter was a warfare vpon the earth, ſo your liues that are Chriſtians, muſt be a warfare vpon the earth. Here we liue in a ſea of troubles. The Sea is the world, the waues are calamities; the Church is the ſhip; the anchor is hope; the ſailes are loue; the Saintes are paſſingers; the hauen is heauen; and Chriſt is our Pilot.</p>
            <p>Now when the Sea can continue without waues, the ſhip with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out toſſings, and paſſengers not be ſicke vpon the water, then ſhal the Church of God be without triall, but not before. Therefore I beſeech you, beloued in the Lord, promiſe your ſelues no ſecurity in this world, but look ſtill for troubles: and when you haue ſlaine a lyon, look for a beare: and when you haue killed the beare, looke for a <hi>Goliah:</hi> and when you haue ouercome <hi>Goliah,</hi> looke for a <hi>Saul:</hi> and when <hi>Saul</hi> is wounded to death, looke for the <hi>Philiſtims:</hi> that is, when you haue ouercome one trouble, or vanquiſhed one ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, looke ſtill for an other trouble, and for an other enemie, and that vntill you die, and the ſpirit returne to God that gaue it.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
               </label> True it is, that God hath not appointed to all his children, a like meaſure of troubles, but to ſome more, and to ſome leſſe: to ſome after one manner, and to ſome after an other. Yet all muſt haue them, &amp; all muſt continue in the hauing of them, without ſtarting from his Maieſtie. For none muſt look to be more nicely or dain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily handled, then the very naturall Sonne of God himſelfe was, who was the onely darling, and the beſt beloued of his Father. Yet
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:2851:18"/>for all that, his whole life here vpon the earth, was nothing elſe but a continuall croſſe. And therefore let this be our daily meditation, that when we haue borne one trouble, wee doe prepare our hearts to beare an other, &amp; euermore to looke for new troubles, ſo long as we liue here in this world, like new men. And ſo I leaue the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie of the righteous, and come to his deliuerance from his miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, <hi>But the Lord deliuereth him out of them all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here are two points to be ſtood vpon. The perſon, who doth deliuer the righteous, and the thing, from which the righteous is deliuered. But becauſe the time is well neere ſpent, &amp; <hi>Idfruſtra fit, per plura, quod fieri potest per pauciora,</hi> That is done in vaine by more things, which fewer to perfection brings; I will conioyne them both together, and from thence deliuer vnto you this doctrine,
<note place="margin">IEHOVAH</note>that there is no trouble which the righteous haue, but the Lord doth deliuer them out of the ſame. This you may ſee by <hi>Ieremies</hi> words, when he ſaith: <hi>For the Lord will not forſake for euer, but though he ſend affliction, yet wil he haue compaſſion, according to the multitudes of his mercies: ô Lord thou haſt maintained the cauſe of my ſoule: and haſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed my life.</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Iam. 3.31.32.58.</note> This you may ſee by <hi>Eſayes</hi> words, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſaith, <hi>I will not contend for euer, neither will I be alwayes wroth. I haue ſeene his wayes, and will heare him. I will leade him alſo, and reſtore comfort vnto him, and to thoſe that lament him. I create the fruites of the lippes to be peace: peace vnto them that are a farre off, &amp; to them that are neere (ſaith the Lord) for I will heale him.</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Eſai. 57.16.</note>
            </p>
            <p>This you may ſee by <hi>Dauids</hi> words, when hee ſayth, <hi>Beholde his eye is vpon them that feare him, and vpon them that truſt in his mercie, to deliuer their ſoules from death, and to preſerue them in famine.
<note n="o" place="margin">Pſalm. 33.18.</note> This poore man cryed, and the Lord heard him, and ſaued him out of all his trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles.
<note n="p" place="margin">Pſal. 34.6.</note> The Lord preſerueth the ſimple, I was in miſcrie, and hee ſaued me. Returne vnto thy reſt ô my ſoule, for the Lord hath bene beneficiall vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee: becauſe thou haſt deliuered my ſoule from death, mine eyes from teares, and my feete from falling, I ſhall walke before the Lord in the land of the liuing.
<note n="q" place="margin">Pſalm. 116.6.</note> The Lord vpholdeth all that fall, and lifteth vp all that are ready to fall. The Lord is neere to all that call vpon him: yea, to all that call vpon him in Truth: hee will fulfill the deſire of them that feare him. Hee alſo will will heare theyr crye and ſaue them. The Lord preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth all that loue him.</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">pſal. 145, 14.18.</note>
            </p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:2851:19"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Then they cryed to the Lorde in their trouble, and he deliuered them from their distreſſe, and led them forth by the right way, that they might goe to a Citie of habitation.</hi>
               <note n="s" place="margin">pſal. 107.6.7.</note> This you may ſee by <hi>Pauls</hi> words, when hee ſaith: <hi>But thou haſt fully knowne my doctrine, maner of liuing, purpoſe, faith, long ſuffering, loue, patience, perſecutions,</hi> and <hi>afflictions, which came vnto me at Antiochia, at Iconium,</hi> and <hi>at Lyſtra, which perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons I ſuffered, but from them all the Lord deliuered me.</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">2 Tim. 3:10.11.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Finally, this you may ſee by many particular examples, <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> was in exile: <hi>Lot</hi> was in captiuity: <hi>Iob</hi> was in bodily extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty:
<note place="margin">See more for this in my Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons on the ſecond pſalme page. 24.</note> 
               <hi>Ioſeph</hi> was in priſon: <hi>Moſes</hi> was in the water: <hi>Ieremy</hi> was in the dungion: <hi>Dauiel</hi> was in the Lions denne: <hi>Ionah</hi> was in the whales belly: <hi>Mordecay</hi> was in the power of <hi>Hamon: Peter</hi> was in the Gaile: the three children were in the burning furnace: and <hi>Iſrael</hi> was in the bondage of <hi>Aegipt:</hi> yet all theſe were deliuered, and came out of their troubles, euery one of them. So that wee may conclude this point with the ſaying of <hi>Dauid,</hi> in theſe words: <hi>For the Lord loueth iudgement, and forſaketh not his ſaints, they ſhall be preſerued for euermore: marke the vpright man, and behold the iuſt, for the ende of that man is peace; the ſaluation of the righteous men ſhall be of the Lord, he ſhall be their ſtrength in the time of trouble, for the Lord ſhall helpe them, and deliuer them, he ſhall deliuer them from the wicked, and ſhall ſaue them, becauſe they truſt in him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
               </label> But here it may be obiected,
<note n="v" place="margin">pſal. 37.28.37.39.40.</note> that the righteous are not alwayes deliuered out of their troubles, but doe now and then continue in them ſtill, and doe rather miſcarry by them, then euer come out from them, conſidering that they die and periſh through them.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> For anſwere herevnto, you muſt know three things; The firſt is, that God hath appointed times when to deliuer his out of their troubles, as it is ſaid in the <hi>Pſalme, Hee ſent a man before them. Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph was ſold for a ſlaue: They held his feete in the ſtockes, and he was layd in irons vntill his appointed time came, and the counſell of the Lord had tryed him.</hi>
               <note n="w" place="margin">pſal. 105.17.</note> The ſecond is, that ſmall and ſhort troubles will not amend ſome, and fit them well, either for the worſhip of their God, while they be here, or for their owne actuall enterance in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the kingdome of heauen hereafter, they are ſo ſeated in their ſinnes, and ſo double died in their tranſgreſſions. And therefore
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:2851:19"/>the Lord is compelled as it were, for his owne glorie, and their good, to continue them ſtill in their afflictions, vntill hee hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued them, &amp; made them tractable to his voyce.
<note place="margin">Read more of this in my 1. ſermon vpon the ſecond pſalme,</note> The third and the laſt is, that theſe that end their liues by their troubles, are moſt of al deliuered from their troubles, becauſe then they are no more mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſted with any trouble, but preſently doe enter into their ioy of reſt, as <hi>Iohn</hi> doth ſhew, ſaying; <hi>Bleſſed are the dead, which dye in the Lord, euen ſo ſaith the ſpirite, for they reſt from their labours, and theyr workes doo follow them.</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">1. Cor. 14.13.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>
               </label> But to paſſe the doctrine, and the doubt which hath bene mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued againſt the doctrine, let vs now come to the reaſons of the doctrine, and ſearch what are the cauſes why the Lord doth deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the righteous out of all their troubles, who are ſubiect to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny troubles. In few words, they are foure in number. The firſt is, becauſe they loue him, according to that which is in the Pſalme, in theſe words, <hi>Becauſe he hath loued me, therfore will I deliuer him, I will exalt him becauſe hee hath knowne my Name, hee ſhall call vpon me and I will heare him. I will be with him in trouble, and I will deliuer him, and glorifie him with long life: I will ſatisfie him, and ſhew him my ſaluation.</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">Pſal. 91, 14</note> The ſecond is, becauſe he doth loue them, and is bound vnto them by his promiſe; according to that which is in <hi>Deuteronomie,</hi> in theſe wordes: <hi>The Lord did not ſet his loue vpon you, nor chooſe you, becauſe you were more in number then any people: for you were the fewest of all people. But becauſe the Lord loued you, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee would keepe the Oath which hee had ſworne vnto your Fathers, the Lord hath brought you out by a mightie hand, and deliuered you out of the houſe of bondage, from the hand of Pharach king of Aegipt.</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">Deut. 7.7, 8</note>
            </p>
            <p>The third is, becauſe he is touched with their grieuances, and all their troubles doe trouble him, according to that which is in <hi>Eſay,</hi> in theſe words: <hi>In all their troubles he was troubled, and the Angell of his preſence ſaued them, in his loue and in his mercie, he redeemed them, and he bore them, and carried them alwayes continually.</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Eſay, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 9</note> Heerevn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to adde that whith is in Iudges; <hi>His ſoule was grieued for the miſery of Iſrael.</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Iudg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> The fourth and laſt is, becauſe he hath glory and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour by their deliuerance, according to that which is in <hi>Ezechiel,</hi> in theſe words: <hi>But I fauoured mine holy Name, which the houſe of Iſrael had polluted among the heathen, whither they went. Therefore ſay
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:2851:20"/>vnto the houſe of Iſrael. Thus ſaith the Lord God, I doe not this for your ſakes, ô houſe of Iſrael, but for my holy names ſake, which you polluted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the heathen, whither you went. And I will ſanctify my great name, which was polluted among the heathen, whom you haue polluted, and the heathen ſhall know that I am the Lord; ſaith the Lord God, when I ſhall be ſanctified in you before their eyes, for I will take you from among the heathen, and gather you out of all countries, and will bring you
<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 16.22.</note> into your owne land.</hi> Herevnto you may well ioyne that which is in <hi>Eſay,</hi> where he ſaith: <hi>For my Names ſake will I deferre my wrath, and for my praiſe will I refraine it from thee, that I cut thee not off. Behold I haue fined thee, but not as ſiluer; I haue choſen thee in the furnace of afflictions: for mine owne ſake, for mine owne ſake will I doe it; for how ſhould my name be polluted? ſurely I will not giue my glory vnto another.</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Eſa. 48.9.10.11</note> So that his loue, his promiſe, his feeling, and his glory, together with their loue &amp; goodnes, doe ſtirre God vp to helpe the righteous, and to deliuer them out of all their troubles. The conſideration whereof may afford vnto vs plentifull obſeruations.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> The firſt is, that God muſt haue the praiſe and honour of all theſe deliuerances, which the godly haue at any time. They muſt aſcribe nothing to themſelues or to others therin, but all to God, as <hi>Moſes</hi> did:
<note n="e" place="margin">Exod. 15.1.</note> as <hi>Deborah</hi> did:
<note n="f" place="margin">Iudg. 5.1.</note> as <hi>Samuel</hi> did:
<note n="g" place="margin">1. Sam. 12.8.</note> as <hi>Dauid</hi> did:
<note n="h" place="margin">Pſalm. 12.4.</note> as <hi>Iehoſophat</hi> did:
<note n="i" place="margin">2. Chro. 20.26.</note> as <hi>Daniel</hi> did:
<note n="k" place="margin">Dan. 6.22.</note> as <hi>Paul</hi> did:
<note n="l" place="margin">2. Tim. 3.11.</note> &amp; as all muſt doe,
<note n="m" place="margin">Pſalm. 107.16.</note> 
               <hi>Praiſed be the Lord,</hi> ſaid <hi>Dauid, euen the God of our ſaluation, which leadeth vs daily with benefits, this is our God, euen the God that ſaueth vs, and to the Lord God belong the iſſues of death.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine he ſaith, <hi>praiſe ye the Lord, for his mercy endureth for euer. Let them which haue beene redeemed of the Lord, ſhew how he hath deliuered them from the hand of the oppreſſor, and gathered them out of the lands, from the Eaſt, and from the Weſt, from the North,
<note n="n" place="margin">Pſalm. 6.68.19.</note> and from the South.</hi> And he doth often repeate this ſaying in the ſame Pſalme: <hi>Let them therefore confeſſe before the Lord his louing kindeneſſe, and his won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull workes before the ſonnes of men.</hi> That is euer true, which is in <hi>Hoſeah,</hi> where the Lord doth ſay; <hi>O Iſrael, one hath deſtroyed thee: but in mee is thy helpe.</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Hdſ: 13.9.</note> For this cauſe I beſeech you (beloued brethren) let none of vs ſacrifice vnto our owne net, or burne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe vnto our owne yarne, but whenſoeuer any of vs are deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out of any danger or diſtreſſe, let vs bleſſed the Name of the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:2851:20"/>Lord our God for the ſame, and put that in practiſe, which is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of vs by the prophet <hi>Dauid,</hi> when he ſaith; <hi>Yee ſonnes of the mighty, giue vnto the Lord glory and ſtrength giue vnto the Lord glory due vnto his Name, worſhippe the Lord in his glorious Sanctuary.</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Pſalm. 29.1.2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond is, that in all troubles the righteous muſt runne to God, they muſt ſeeke him out, and labour to haue his fauour and aſſiſtance. They muſt not looke vnto themſelues, or reſt vpon their owne ſtrength: for they are weake, and vnable for to helpe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. That which Chriſt ſaid in one ſenſe, is true in this. <hi>Without mee yee can doe nothing.</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Ioh. 15.5.</note> Neither muſt they look to man, for all the world is againſt them.
<note n="r" place="margin">Ioh. 15.19.</note> But they muſt looke to the Lord their God, ſaying with <hi>Iſrael, Come, and let vs returne vnto the Lord; For he hath ſpoyled, and he will heale vs: he hath wounded vs, and he will binde vs vp: after two dayes will hee reuiue vs, and in the third day he will raiſe vs vp, and wee ſhall liue in his ſight.</hi>
               <note n="s" place="margin">Hoſ: 6.1.2.</note> Saying with <hi>Iehoſhaphat,</hi> when the <hi>Moabites, Ammonites,</hi> and the <hi>Idumeans</hi> of <hi>Mount-Seir</hi> came to bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell againſt him; <hi>O our God wilt thou not iudge them? For there is no ſtrength in vs to ſtand before this great multitude that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth againſt vs: neither doe we know what to doe, but our eyes are towards thee.</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">2. Chron. 2.20.</note> Saying with <hi>Dauid, Haue mercie vpon mee ô GOD, haue mercie vpon me, for my ſoule truſteth in thee, and in the ſhaddow of thy wings will I truſt, till theſe afflictions ouerpaſſe, I will call vpon the most high GOD, euen to the God that performeth his promiſe towards me: He will ſend from heauen &amp; ſaue mo fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the reproofe of him that would ſwallow me.</hi> Selah, <hi>God wil ſend his mercie &amp; truth.</hi>
               <note n="v" place="margin">Pſalm. 57.10.</note> Saying with <hi>Aſa,</hi> when the <hi>Aethyopians</hi> came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him with an Hoaſt of ten hundred thouſand, and three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred charrets; <hi>Lord it is nothing with thee to helpe with many, or with no power: helpe vs, ô Lord our God: for we reſt on thee, and in thy Name, are we come againſt this multitude, O Lord thou art our God, let not man pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile againſt thee.</hi>
               <note n="w" place="margin">2. Chro. 14.11.</note> Saying with Herechia: <hi>O lord God of Iſrael, which dwelleſt between the Cherubims, thou art very God alone, ouer all the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of the earth: Lord bow down thine eare &amp; heare: Lord open thine eyes, and behold and heare the words of</hi> Sanacherib, <hi>who hath ſent to blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme the liuing God. Now therefore, ô Lord our God, I beſeech thee ſaue thou vs out of his hand, that all the kingdomes of the earth may knowe that thou ô Lord art onely God.</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">2. King. 19.10.16.19.</note> Saying laſtly, with the godly in the pſalme, <hi>I lift vp mine eyes to thee that dwelleſt in the heauens. Behold, as
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:2851:21"/>the eyes of ſeruants looke vnto the hand of their maiſters, and as the eyes of a maiden vnto the ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d of her miſtris: So our eyes wayte vpon the lord our God, vntill he haue mercie vpon vs.</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">Pſal: 123.1.2.</note> O my brethren, there is much gadding abroad, but I beſeech you let vs not wander, as others do therein. We muſt not with <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> relie vpon enchaunters: Wee muſt not with <hi>Saul</hi> relye vpon witches: we muſt not with <hi>Aſa</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye vpon phyſitions: we muſt not with <hi>Iſrael</hi> rely vpon the <hi>Aegip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians:</hi> we muſt not with <hi>Iezabel</hi> relie vpon Idols: we muſt not with papiſts relie vpon the dead, or canonized ſaints: we muſt not with the worldling, relie vpon the wedge of golde, or earthly wealth: we muſt not in a word with <hi>Goliah,</hi> relie vpon our own ſtrength or power: But we muſt relye vpon the Lord our God. We I ſay, who are profeſſors, who are Chriſtians, who are the viſible members of the Church, who are the true children of God,
<note place="margin">Gol.</note>euen all wee, I ſay muſt relie onely vpon the Lord our God, whatſoeuer others doe beſides.
<note place="margin">Sother. Ereptor.</note> Surely he onely muſt be our <hi>Goel;</hi> our <hi>Soter;</hi> our <hi>Ereptor;</hi> that is, our Redeemer: our Sauiour: our deliuerer. Hee muſt bee our ſtrength, our refuge, our ſhield, our rock, our fortreſſe, and the horne of our ſaluation. As <hi>Dauid</hi> doth ſpeake in the 18. Pſalme, and 2. verſe. And therfore I pray, let vs do euermore as that good man did, who ſaid: <hi>Whom haue I in heauen but thee? &amp; I haue deſired none in the earth with thee. My fleſh faileth, and mine heart alſo but God is the ſtrength of mine heart, and my portion for euer. For loe they that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw themſelues from thee ſhall periſh: thou deſtroyeſt all them that goe a whoring from thee. As for me, it is good for me to draw neer to God. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I haue put my truſt in the Lord, that I may declare all thy works.</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">Pſalm. 73.24.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The third is a comfort vnto the righteous againſt all their trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels. <hi>Reioyce ô daughter Zion</hi> (ſaith <hi>Zophonie) be ye ioyfull, ô Iſrael; be glad and reioyce with all thine hart, ô daughter Ieruſalem. The Lord hath taken away thy iudgements: he hath caſt out thine enemie, the king of Iſrael, euen the Lord is in the middeſt of thee, thou ſhalt ſee no more e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill:
<note n="a" place="margin">Zeph. 3.14.</note> Feare not</hi> (ſaid God vnto <hi>Iſrael</hi> his people) <hi>for I am with thee, be not affraid, for I am thy God, I will ſtrengthen thee, and help thee, and will ſuſtaine thee with the right hand of my iuſtice. Behold all they that prouoke thee, ſhall be aſhamed and confounded, they ſhall be as nothing, and they that ſtriue with thee ſhall periſh.</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Eſa. 41.10.</note> Doubtles as <hi>Dauid</hi> gaue charge vnto the ſouldiers, that they ſhould not kill <hi>Abſolom</hi> his
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:2851:21"/>ſonne, though he ſent them againſt <hi>Abſolom</hi> to ſtay his rebellion: ſo God doth command croſſes not to deſtroy his childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, though he ſend them againſt his children, either to correct them, or to trie them. And therefore as the viper lept vpon <hi>Paul,</hi> and lept of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, ſo troubles leape vpon the righteous and leaps off againe, as though they had miſtaken the partie, and rapt at the wrong doore. Looke then how all the accuſers went out, one by one, beginning at the eldeſt, euen to the laſt, and left the poore adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſſe woman alone onely with Chriſt, there being not ſo much as any one left behinde, either to condemne her, or to ſtone her with ſtones:
<note n="c" place="margin">Iohn. 8.9.</note> So doe all troubles vaniſh away from the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, one by one, and leaue them, ſafe and alone without one, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to vexe them, or to deſtroy them with deſtructions. For be it, that the lawier cannot deliuer his client but from his ſtrife: the Phyſition his patient but fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his ſicknes: the maiſter his ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t but from his bondage: the father his childe but from his pouerty: the tutor his ſcholler but from his ignorance: the captaine his ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er but from his wounds: yet God can and will alſo deliuer his from all their troubles whatſoeuer. And howſoeuer theſe their troubles doe come in a thouſand waies, like waters through ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny grates, yet he can and will alſo meete with them all. For hee can worke, &amp; doth alſo often worke, by meanes, without meanes: and contrary to all meanes.</p>
            <p>By meanes, yea by weake meanes, he ſaued <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when hee ouerthrew the innumerable army of the <hi>Midianites</hi> by <hi>Gedeons</hi> three hundred men.
<note n="d" place="margin">Iudg. 9.7.</note> By meanes, yea by weake meanes, he ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued <hi>Saul</hi> and his people, when he ſlew a garriſon of the philiſtins by <hi>Ionathan,</hi> and his armorbearer.
<note n="e" place="margin">1. Cor. 14.</note> By meanes, yea by weake meanes, he ſaued <hi>Lot,</hi> when he conquered <hi>Chadorlaomor,</hi> &amp; three other kings with him, by <hi>Abraham</hi> and his familie.
<note n="f" place="margin">Geneſ. 14.</note> Laſtly by meanes, yea by weake meanes, he ſaued the nation of the Iewes, when he deſtroyed <hi>Goliah by Dauid. Siſera</hi> by <hi>Iael, and Abimilech by a woman.</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">1. Sam. 17. Iud. 4. &amp; 9.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Without meanes he ſaued <hi>Iehoſophat</hi> and his people, when hee himſelfe did ouerthrow the <hi>Moabites,</hi> the <hi>Ammonites,</hi> and them of mount <hi>Seir,</hi> which made warre againſt them.
<note n="h" place="margin">2. Chron. 20.</note> Without meanes he ſaued <hi>Moſes</hi> and his people, when he himſelfe drowned <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roah</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:2851:22"/>and his army in the red ſea, purſuing after them: without meanes he ſaued <hi>Ezechiah</hi> and his people,
<note n="i" place="margin">Exod. 14.</note> when he himſelfe ſlew the huge army of the <hi>Aſſirians,</hi> who came with a purpoſe to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy them.
<note n="k" place="margin">2. King. 17.</note> Laſtly, without means he ſaued <hi>Eliſha,</hi> and his man, when he himſelfe ſmote with blindnes the <hi>Syrians,</hi> who beſieged <hi>Dothan,</hi> the city where the prophet was, and came to take him.
<note n="l" place="margin">2. King. 6.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Contrary to all meanes, hee ſaued the three children from bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, being in the fire.
<note n="m" place="margin">Dan. 3.</note> Contrary to all means, he ſaued <hi>Ionah</hi> from conſuming, being in the Whales belly.
<note n="n" place="margin">Ion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 2.</note> Contrary to all meanes, he ſaued <hi>Daniel</hi> from deuouring, being in the Lions den.
<note n="o" place="margin">Dan. 6.</note> Finally, contrary to all meanes, be ſaued the <hi>Iſralites</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, being in the bottome of the ſea.
<note n="p" place="margin">Ezod. 14.</note> Wherefore my beloued brethren, faint not whatſoeuer your troubles be, but be of a good comfort, and cheere vp your harts in the Lord, &amp; doubt nothing, but all ſhall be well with you in the end. Oh ſay with <hi>Dauid,</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your harts are diſquieted, <hi>Why art thou caſt downe my ſoule? and why art thou diſquieted within me? waite on God, for I will yet giue him thanks, he is my preſent helpe and my God.</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Pſalm. 42.11.</note> Doubtles he will come, he will come, waite but a little, and you ſhall ſee your deliuerance. And ſo I conclude this worthy obſeruation with the prophets needful exhortation, in theſe words: <hi>Hope in the Lord, be ſtrong, and he ſhall comfort thine heart, and truſt in the Lord.</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Pſalm. 27.14.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The fourth and laſt, is an Inſtruction to the world, to warne them in their euill courſes, that they goe not about to trouble the righteous, and to qualifie them in their ioyfull mirth, that they doe not exult too much in the miſery of the righteous. For ſeeing that the Lord will deliuer the righteous out of all their troubles, it is a great folly for the world to goe about to trouble them, and a greater vanity in them to reioyce at their troubles, as though they ſhould continue euer in their troubles, and neuer ſee an end of their troubles. Here, here, let the wicked remember what is in <hi>Zophonie,</hi> when the Lord ſaith, <hi>After a certaine time will I gather the afflicted, that were of thee, and them that beare the reproach for it: behold at that time I will bruiſe all that afflict thee, and I will ſaue her that hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, and gather her that was caſt out, and I will giue them praiſe, and fame in all the lands, of their ſhame.</hi>
               <note n="s" place="margin">Zoph. 3.18.19</note> Here, here, let the wicked remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber what is in <hi>Eſay,</hi> where the almighty ſaith: <hi>But thus ſaith the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:2851:22"/>Lord, euen the captiuity of the mighty ſhall be taken away, and the prey of the tyrant ſhall be deliuered, for I will contend with him that contendeth with thee, and I will ſaue thy children: And will feede them that ſpoile thee with their owne fleſh, and they ſhall be drunken with their owne blood, as with ſweete wine, and all fleſh ſhall know, that I the Lord am thy ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our and thy redeemer, the mighty one of Iacob.</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Eſai. 49.25.26</note> Here, here, let the wicked remember what is in the Prouerbes, when <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>The righteous eſcapeth out of trouble, and the wicked ſhall come in his fleede.
<note n="v" place="margin">Pro. 11 8.</note> Againe, the wicked ſhall be a ranſome for the iuſt, and the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſor for the righteous.</hi>
               <note n="w" place="margin">Prou. 21.18.</note> Here, here, laſtly, let the wicked remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber what is in <hi>Micha,</hi> when the prophet ſaith, <hi>Reioyce not againſt me, ô mine enemie; though I fall, I ſhall ariſe when I ſhall ſit in darknes, the Lord ſhall be a light vnto me, I will beare the wrath of the Lord, becauſe I haue ſinned againſt him, vntill he plead my cauſe, and execute iudgement for me. Then will he bring me forth to the light, and I ſhall ſee his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes. Then ſhe that is mine enemy, ſhall looke vpon it, and ſhame ſhall couer her, which ſaid vnto me, where is the Lord thy God? mine eyes ſhall behold her: now ſhall ſhe be troden downe as the mire of the ſtreetes.</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Mic. 7.8.9.10.</note> Hitherto you haue had, welbeloued in the Lord, ſuch things one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as concerned my text, and which in a generall manner flowed out of the ſame for the good of vs all. But now I pray giue mee leaue in a few words to make ſome particular application thereof vnto that honourable and moſt worthy perſon, our moſt high and mighty king, for whoſe ſake we are here this day aſſembled toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. You are not ignorant how his troubles haue bene many: neither are you ignorant how his deliuerances alſo haue bene ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie. Out of all doubt, that which <hi>Dauid</hi> doth here ſay, his Maieſty may truly ſay: <hi>Many are the troubles of the righteous, but the Lord doth deliuer him out of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all.</hi> For he hath had good experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both in his own perſon. But not to ſpeake of al, but only of one thing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them all: You know, that as vpon this day heeretofore in <hi>Scotla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d,</hi> his Highnes was neer vnto his death, but the Lord did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer him fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that his death. <hi>Alexa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der Ruthwen,</hi> one of the <hi>Gowryes,</hi> the Earls own brother, through a wicked traine, drew his Ma: into a little ſtudy, in the Earles owne houſe, the plotter of that treaſon: to the which none could come for his reſcue, it was ſo far remote, and ſo many dores were faſt lock't betwixt them. In that ſtudy he
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:2851:23"/>had ſet a man with a weapon, a dagger at his girdle. They three on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly being now in the ſtuddy, and the ſtuddy-doore faſt lockt vpon them, <hi>Alexander</hi> put on his hat on his head, and drawing the dag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger from that other mans gyrdle, held the point of it to the Kings breaſt, avowing now that the King behooued to be in his will, and to be vſed as he liſt, ſwearing many bloody oaths, that if the King cryed one word, or opened a window to looke out, that dagger ſhould preſently goe to his heart, affirming that hee was ſure, that now the Kings conſcience was burdned for murdring his father.</p>
            <p>Behold, here was one part of his highnes trouble. Now marke how the Lord did deliuer him from the ſame. Firſt, hee made the man there ſet, to do nothing but to tremble and quake, and to beg <hi>Alexander</hi> (for Gods ſake) not to meddle with his Maieſtie, nor to doe him any harme. Secondly he ſtayde <hi>Alexander,</hi> that hee thruſt not at all at the King with his weapon. Thirdly he put into the K: mouth ſuch an holy and powerfull ſpeach, and directed his tongue, with ſuch a perſwaſiue language, that <hi>Alex:</hi> himſelf appeared to be ſomwhat amazed, and vncouering his head againe, ſwore and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted, that his Maieſties life ſhould be ſafe, if hee would behaue himſelf quietly without making noyſe or crying: &amp; that he would onely bring in the Earle his brother, to ſpeake with his Maieſtie. And ſo he went forth vnto his brother, looking the dore behinde him, and leauing his Ma: with that man he ſound there before him. To proceede, back againe comes <hi>Alex:</hi> to the King, with a ſword at his ſide, after that he had talked with the earle his brother; and at his incomming to his Maieſtie, he did caſt his hands abroade in a deſperate manner, and ſaid, <hi>hee could not mend it, his Maieſtie beho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to dye:</hi> And with that, offered a garter to binde his Maieſties hands, with ſwearing, <hi>hee behooued to be bound.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Behold, here was an other part of his highnes trouble, now marke how the Lord did deliuer him from the ſame. Firſt, he cauſed the man that remained with the King, to do nothing againſt the King, as before, but in the abſence of <hi>Alexander,</hi> when he went to talke with his brother, He opened the ſtuddy-window at the requeſt of the K: which was a benefite vnto the King. Secondly, he did ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſotte <hi>Alexander,</hi> that he left the ſtuddy doore vnlockt, at his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in at this time for haſte, &amp; did not goe about to kill the King
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:2851:23"/>with his weapon, but to bind him with his garter. Thirdly, he gaue that ſtrength and ability to the King, that he was hard enough for <hi>Alexander,</hi> &amp; with ſtruggling drew him out of the ſtuddy. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, he directed the Kings traine to come vnder the ſtuddy window, at the ſame time, when the King and <hi>Alexander</hi> were griping togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who heard and knewe the Kings voyce, crying out, <hi>that they were murthering him, in that traſonable forme.</hi> Fiftly, he moued the ſaid K: traine to retire, and in returning, hee cauſed ſome of them to hit vpon an open way (which was a turn-peck-doore, prouided onely for the Earle and his ſeruants, as appeared for that purpoſe. For e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer before it was wont to be ſhut, and was onely then left open) to come immediately to the King. Laſtly, he cauſed <hi>Sir Iohn Ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſey</hi> (after he was entred into the chamber, and had found his Mai: and <hi>Alexander</hi> ſtrugling togither) to ſtrike <hi>Alex:</hi> with his dagger, ſome two or three times: &amp; taking him by the ſhoulders, to throw him down the ſtaires: who was no ſooner ſhut out at the doore, but was met by <hi>Sir Thomas Erskin,</hi> &amp; <hi>Sir Hugh Hereis,</hi> who there vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſtaires ended him. To conclude this point, no ſooner could the ſaid <hi>Syr Thomas Erskine,</hi> &amp; <hi>Syr Hugh Hereis</hi> with an other ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant enter into the chamber where his Maieſtie was, but that the ſaid Earle of <hi>Gowrie</hi> (before they could get the dore ſhut) follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them in at the backe, hauing caſt him directly to come vp that priuie paſſage, as is before ſaide, who at his firſt entrie, hauing a drawne ſword in euery hand, and a ſteele bonnet on his head, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with ſeuen of his ſeruants, euery one of them hauing in like manner, a drawne ſword, <hi>Cryed out with a great Oath, that they ſhould all dye as Traytors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Behold here was an other part of his highnes trouble: now marke how the Lord did deliuer him from the ſame. Firſt he mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the harts of his ſeruants to ſhut his maieſtie backe into the lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſtudie, and the doord ſhut vpon him, that ſo he might be put in ſafely from all ſtrokes. Secondly hee gaue them that courage and ſtrength, that though they were but foure againſt eight, yet they durſt encounter with the earle and his ſeruants, and after many ſtrokes on all hands got the victory of them, the ſaid Earle of <hi>Gowrie</hi> being ſtricken dead with a ſtroake through the heart, which the ſaid <hi>Sir Iohn Ramſey</hi> gaue him, without once crying vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:2851:24"/>God, and the reſt of his ſeruants dung ouer the ſtaires with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hurts. <hi>So let all thine enemies periſh ô Lord; but they that loue him ſhall be as the ſunne, when he riſeth in his might.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The victory thus going on his maieſties ſide, hee being now ſafe, and his enemies being deſtroyed before him, (howſoeuer they were many, euen to the number of ſome three or foure ſcore, and his company was but ſmall, not aboue fifteene perſons in all, who alſo were without any kind of armour, except ſwords, no not ſo much as daggers and whingers) downe he falles vpon his knees in the midſt of his ſeruants, who alſo kneeled round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout him, euen immediately before he came out of the chamber, and with his owne mouth hee thanked God for that miraculous deliuerance and victory: aſſuring himſelfe, that God had preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued him from ſo deſperate a perill, for the perfitting of ſome great worke behinde to his glory, and for procuring by him the weale of his people, that God had committed to his charge. The which being done, and the whole town of Saint <hi>Iohn Stone</hi> being appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, his maieſtie returned home, with the great ioy, and loue of all ſorts of perſons throughout the land, who triumphed exceeding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for his deliuerance, and gaue manifold thankes vnto the Lord for the ſame. Wherein my beloued brethren, let vs labour to pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralel them, and ſtriue rather therein to goe beyond them, then in any ſort to come behind them. O let vs pray daily vnto the Lord for him, and vpon our knees giue him moſt harty thanks euery day, becauſe we doe enioy him. <hi>Gratious God, we beſeech thee, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer him euermore vnder the ſhaddow of thy hand, make him a choſen ſhaft, and hide him ſtill in thy quiuer. Let him reioyce euer in thy ſtrength and in thy ſaluation, giue him, ô giue him, his harts deſire, and deny him not the requeſt of his lips, preuent him with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iberall bleſſings, and ſet ſtill a crown of pure gold vpon his head. Giue the nations before him, ſubdue the kings that riſe vp againſt him, giue them as duſt to his ſword, and as ſcattered ſtuble to his bow. Let iudgement alſo run downe in his daies, as waters, and righteouſnes, as a mighty riuer; yea let him feede his people according to the ſimplicitie of his heart, and guide them by the diſcretion of his hands. Thus ô Lord, thus ô Lord,</hi> let it be done vnto him, that ſo he may raigne here with vs many yeares proſperouſly, and with thy ſelfe in the heauens for euer triumphantly, to thy glory, and his euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:2851:24"/>happineſſe. <hi>Amon, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now to end all, and to ſpeake a word or two vnto you all by way of application, who are now my preſent Auditory. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you (my beloued brethren) remember what now hath bene deliuered vnto you. Though troubles fall vpon you, yet ſhrinke not, but ſtand faſt, and quiet your ſelues like men. There be many I confeſſe in the world (I wil not ſay amongſt you) who fain would haue a Church (as it were) of ſugar, and a ſpouſe of Roſes. They would feede vpon <hi>Manna,</hi> and tread vpon veluet. In ſeruing of God, they would be ſerued themſelues, and be made free from all afflictions. They loue <hi>Canaan,</hi> but they loath the wildernes. They like the crowne, but they loue not the croſſe. They are like <hi>Iames</hi> and <hi>Iohn,</hi> who ſought to ſit in the ſeate of honor, but not to drinke of the cuppe of afflictions. But the truth is, as you haue heard, and you muſt belieue it, The way to heauen is no eaſie way, it is not ſtrewed with flowers, but it is a ſharpe way, it is ſet with thornes: and happily in your own experience you ſhal finde that to be true, which the Prophet doth here ſay: <hi>Many are the troubles of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous.</hi> Yet be not diſcouraged at it. For firſt, though your troubles be many, yet you are able for to beare them. The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e is no more laid vpon you, then you can carry. God is like a wiſe Phyſition in this caſe, who doth weigh his Drugs, and fitte them according to our ſtrength. <hi>Wee are afflicted on euery ſide</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul) yet are not in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe: in pouertie, but not ouercome of pouertie: wee are perſecuted, but not forſaken: caſt downe, but we periſh not.</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">1. Cor. 4 8.</note> Secondly, though they be many, yet ſomtimes you are alone without them. As you haue a time of faſting, ſo haue you a time of feaſting: as you haue a time of mourning, ſo haue you a time of laughing: as you haue of ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, ſo haue you a time of health: as you haue a time of ſhame, ſo haue you a time of praiſe: in a word, as you haue a time of miſerie, ſo haue you a time of felicitie. Thirdly, though they be many, yet they doe not hurt you, but rather doe you good: you come forth better often from them, then euer you went into them. Conſider with your ſelues how they ſet your wits to ſtudie, your conſcience to examine, your memory to repeate, your will to affect, your heart to pray, your tongue to entreate, your eare to hearken, your foote to goe, your hand to work, &amp; euery member to doe his dutie. Call
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:2851:25"/>to minde alſo, how they doe cauſe you to ſeeke knowledge, to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand Gods promiſes, to ſeek <hi>Faith,</hi> to apprehend Gods promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, to ſeeke <hi>Hope,</hi> to waite for the performance of Gods promiſes, to ſeeke laſtly <hi>Prayer,</hi> to haſten God to accompliſh his promiſes. Fourthly, though they be many, yet you haue deſerued them: yea, more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that, you haue deſerued more then them. <hi>GOD hath not dealt with vs</hi> (ſaith <hi>Dauid) after our ſinnes, nor rewarded vs according to our iniquities.</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Pſalm. 103.10.</note> Fiftly, though they be many, yet you are not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone in them, but others are conioyned with you, in the partaking of them: yea, men and women, I doubt not in your owne iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, better then your ſelues; as you may ſee in <hi>Matth: chapt.</hi> 5.12. and in <hi>Peter,</hi> 1. <hi>Pet:</hi> 4.12.13. Laſtly, though they be many, yet you ſhall not continue ſtill in them, but come forth in time conuenient from them, according to the latter part of my Text, <hi>But the LORD doth deliuer him out of them all.</hi> Marke the word well, <hi>Out of them all.</hi> We ſtartle at the croſſe often, becauſe we are like the Prophets ſeruant, who did ſee his foes, but not his friends. We ſee our ſore, but not our ſalue. Deliuerance ſeemes a farre off like <hi>Abraham</hi> in the Heauens, as though it would neuer come ſo long as we be. But let vs know, and euer remember for our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, that the Lord will come, and deliuer vs: And as <hi>Moſes</hi> would leaue no hoofe behinde him, when hee was to deliuer the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> out of <hi>Aegipt:</hi> ſo when the Lord commeth to deliuer vs: who are his, hee will not leaue a trouble behinde him, but rid vs out of al our troubles. Comfort your ſelues, oh comfort your ſelues, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you, with theſe ſayings; And the God of all grace be euer with you all, to inſtruct you, to direct you, to defend you, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme you, to comfort you, to enrich you: and in a word, to bleſſe and to ſaue you, through <hi>IES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> our <hi>SA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>IOVR;</hi> to whome with the <hi>FATHER,</hi> and the <hi>HOLYGHOST,</hi> one Eternall <hi>GOD,</hi> and three diſtinct perſons, be rendred, as is moſt due, all honour, all glorie, all praiſe, all power, all dominion, and all thanks-giuing, both now and euermore. <hi>Amen. Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:2851:25"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
